<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Comments on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/tags/comments/</link><description>Recent content in Comments on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://minimaxir.com/tags/comments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Quality, Popularity, and Negativity of 5.6 Million Hacker News Comments</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/10/hn-comments-about-comments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/10/hn-comments-about-comments/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Last February, I &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published an article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, a tech-oriented link aggregator run by startup accelerator &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ycombinator.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;. In that post, I analyzed all submissions to date, and noted that the site has a strong and active userbase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent months, however, Hacker News has undergone criticism. A blog post by Danilo Campos titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://danilocampos.com/2014/09/y-combinator-and-the-negative-externalities-of-hacker-news/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Y Combinator and the negative externalities of Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, notes that although Hacker News is a critical resource for young male techies based in Silicon Valley (&lt;em&gt;Disclosure: I am a young male techie based in Silicon Valley&lt;/em&gt;), this has the consequence of excluding female hackers. Campos has even created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%23hnwatch&amp;amp;src=typd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;#HNwatch&lt;/a&gt; hashtag to catalog sexist and insensitive comments made by Hacker News users. As a long-time &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;user on Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, I unfortunately &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir/status/468080907925340160&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;agree with this assessment&lt;/a&gt; at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fairness, such comments are in the minority on Hacker News. Or are they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to better assess the quality, popularity, and negativity of Hacker News comments over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve downloaded 5,592,362 comments from Hacker News, the maximum number of comments possible, from its beginnings in 2006 to October 2014. Hopefully, these comments will answer whether Hacker News is experiencing a rise in quality, or if the complaints levied against HN are valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZwonVX_KlDYhuhPnAAnVpdVRgu4LxldP74-c_kvOd5k/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;glance at Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s best comments&lt;/a&gt;, determined by the number of upvotes it receives from the Hacker News community, for each month since 2006:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZwonVX_KlDYhuhPnAAnVpdVRgu4LxldP74-c_kvOd5k/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are interesting trends in this sample data set. The types of comments that became popular in 2006-2008 Hacker News were one-line quips, akin to those you would see in the comments on modern Reddit (which is a topic for another blog post). Highly-voted comments often come from the same people, especially those from Paul Graham (pg), Founder and then-President of Y Combinator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/early_reddit.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may indicate a bias or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halo_effect&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;halo effect&lt;/a&gt; where the commenter is more impactful than the comment itself. Additionally, some comments received many upvotes due to context: the top comment in December 2010 was simply &amp;ldquo;sad.&amp;rdquo; in a thread about &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2013248&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yahoo Shutting Down Delicious&lt;/a&gt;, but the comment was made by Joshua Schachter (joshu), the creator of Delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare those older comments to those made between 2012-2014. Those comments are very long, insightful, and made by many different people. (including a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4689643&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;comment by Danilo Campos himself&lt;/a&gt; in October 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these are the good comments. The bad comments are &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1IfbSDYVBXiHZCuMdHXgprhmeCVc4XDtOGizF9CSGyUo/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;set of Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s worst comments&lt;/a&gt; from each month where the comment has received a score of -3 or -4, the lowest score before the comment is automatically killed. (&lt;em&gt;Warning: comments may cause you to lose faith in humanity and/or be unintentionally hilarious&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1IfbSDYVBXiHZCuMdHXgprhmeCVc4XDtOGizF9CSGyUo/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The types of bad comments haven&amp;rsquo;t changed over the years. Hostile comments are immediately downvoted. It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that on Hacker News, you can be downvoted for being factually wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some users are more active commenters than others. Out of Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s 176,692 users who have made atleast 1 comment, only 48% of those commenters end up leaving two more comments, and only 6% of HN users end up leaving 100 or more comments total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/n-comments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as users comment more on Hacker News and learn the intricacies of HN&amp;rsquo;s culture, they become more skilled at creating quality comments which receive higher scores, which serve as an indicator of quality. As Hacker News users comment more and more, the average expected comment score for each successive post increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/n-comments-practice.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(The faded area for all charts in this article represents a 95% confidence interval for the average at a given point; all of the confidence intervals are very narrow due to the sheer quantity of data present. Whoo, big data!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the trends behind the Hacker News comments? First, we must see how Hacker News comments has changed over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hacking-through-the-years&#34;&gt;Hacking Through The Years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one would expect, the number of new comments posted on Hacker News each month has been gradually increasing proportional to its popularity, although the number of new comments per month has decreased starting in 2014, which indicates a slowing growth rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_total_comments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, has Hacker News retained quality with its increasing notoriety? One way to check is to analyze the average amount of points of the comments. Hacker News comments start out at 1 point, and other users can upvote and downvote comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_average_points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimum average points score of any given comment was about 2 points, meaning that all comments received atleast 1 upvote on average. This trend has been increasing until 2011 when it peaked at about 4.5 points. Since then, the average has trended downward, with a particularly large drop starting at 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, starting in 2014, both quantity &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; quality are on a downward trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to gauge quality is to look at the average comment length. Are comments trending toward short quips, or are longform comments more popular?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_average_words.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The length of the average comment has increased by about 10% over the years, which shows a slight increase in the overall thoughtfulness of HN comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has the average sentiment on Hacker News changed over the years? To gauge the relative sentiment of Hacker News comments, I compared each word of the comment against a lexicon of positive/negative words, and counted the number of review words in the lexicon. In this case, I used the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.uic.edu/~liub/FBS/sentiment-analysis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;lexicons compiled by UIC professor Bing Liu&lt;/a&gt;. This is the same method used in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/one-star-five-stars/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous analysis of Yelp reviews&lt;/a&gt;, where the technique was very effective. However, unlike Yelp, comments on Hacker News tend to make use of sarcasm, so this method may be less effective. (there isn&amp;rsquo;t any easy method for detecting sarcasm, because who in the entire world would want an easy method for detecting sarcasm?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that, we can calculate average positivity and average negativity for a given comment by dividing the number of positive/negative words respectively by the approximate number of words in the comment. Both metrics have converged slightly over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_average_positive_negative.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, the average positivity of a comment is &lt;em&gt;3.2%&lt;/em&gt;, while the average negativity of a comment is &lt;em&gt;2.3%&lt;/em&gt; (leading to a 0.9% net positive sentiment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of the comments Hacker News has definitely changed since the site&amp;rsquo;s humble beginnings in 2006, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to determine if it&amp;rsquo;s for the &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look more into the nature of the upvote system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-points&#34;&gt;Free Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, the number of points on a new Hacker News comment starts at 1 point. Anyone can give an upvote, which increases the points value by one. However, long-time HN users can downvote posts, decreasing the score by 1. Downvoting has another effect; comments with 0 or fewer points turn an aesthetically-displeasing gray, in an effort to both hide them from the public eye and encourage corrective upvotes if necessary from users with OCD. In all other cases, the points score of a comment is hidden from other users in order to help prevent bandwagoning and the upvoting of comments just because they have lots of upvotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/distribution_comment_points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over 50% of all comments simply have 1 or 2 points, with the proportion decreasing by a third for each successive point value. What&amp;rsquo;s surprising is how few comments have 0 or fewer points: this shows that HN users do not like downvoting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that comment length could be used a proxy for comment quality. Is there a relationship between the number of points a comment receives and the length of a comment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/distribution_comment_points_words.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, yes! The effect of comment length on the number of points a comment received is likely not solely causal, but the correlation between the two values is helpful. (it is statistically unlikely to receive a lot of upvotes if your comment is short. The inverse is also true; a short comment is much more likely get downvoted.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a similar correlation between sentiment and the number of points a comment receives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/distribution_comment_points_sentiment.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope. Both positivity and negativity are relatively static regardless of point values, although it&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that comments with 0 or fewer points (downvoted comments) have a disproportionately high negativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tone-and-tolerance-on-hacker-news&#34;&gt;Tone and Tolerance on Hacker News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a big difference between the language used in a Hacker News comment on a typical submission, and the language used in Hacker News submissions about women and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/hn_2_gram_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This word cloud consists of bigrams made from 109k comments from HN submissions in September 2014, and from 21k comments in threads whose submission title contains &amp;ldquo;women&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;female,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;diversity.&amp;rdquo; The language in the former is more neutral and about the content of the article (apparently Hacker News users &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like to talk about Open Source software), while the submissions about gender and diversity trend to talk about tangent topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does the tone differ between the two groups of articles? Here&amp;rsquo;s the distribution of the average number of positive words in comments per submission in September 2014:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/density_september_2014_hn.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average amount of positive words in a comment made in September 2014 is 2.16 words, and the average amount of negative words is 1.46, with both of those values being close to the respective statistical modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s compare that to the distribution of comments made on all submissions about women and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/density_women.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average amount of positive words in a comment made in thread about gender and diversity is 2.48 words, a little higher than the average, and is also the most frequently occuring value. However, The average amount of positive words in a comment made in thread about gender and diversity is 2.10 words, a much higher increase. The average is to the right of the mode, indicating that the average is skewed-right by submissions with overly-negative comments. This may be why there is a greater perception of negativity for readers of comment threads about women and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/hackernews.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;stated goals of Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; is to avoid an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eternal_September&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eternal September&lt;/a&gt;, where the quality of discourse drops and everyone leaves. It&amp;rsquo;s clear that the quality of discourse has changed over the years: comments are longer, but not necessarily better. Positivity has decreased and negativity has increased. The difference between 2006 HN and 2014 HN is stark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News isn&amp;rsquo;t the perfect tech news aggregator. The issue of inclusion is real, and despite the fact that sexist comments are in the minority, they need to stop. In 2014, both quantity &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; quality are decreasing. But since that Y Combinator has &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ycombinator.com/diversity-and-startups&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;committed to ending sexism in tech&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ycombinator.com/meet-the-people-taking-over-hacker-news&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;appointed new moderators&lt;/a&gt; to control content quality, I&amp;rsquo;m confident that things will improve in the future for Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data was retrieved from Hacker News using &lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/api&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the official API&lt;/a&gt;. The data was then stored in a PostgreSQL database, mostly so I could take advantage of that database&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.1/static/tutorial-window.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;window functions&lt;/a&gt; capability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charts, word clouds, and other miscellaneous data processing was done using R and ggplot2. Gathering the data from the API and extracting the bigrams for the word clouds was done using Python.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can access the code used to process the data, chart the data, and extract bigrams from the comments in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/hacker-news-comment-analysis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. This does not include the code for retrieving the comments from the Hacker News API and storing it in PostgreSQL: that code will be in a separate repository if released.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Blog Comment System That Steals Comments From Facebook</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2013/05/comments-everywhere/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2013 21:59:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2013/05/comments-everywhere/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of the LiveFyre comments system for blogs. As I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about before, LiveFyre is difficult to use, and actually hurts blogs more than it helps. But more and more blogs, such as CNet and AllThingsD, have switched to LiveFyre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AllThingsD&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://allthingsd.com/20130330/introducing-livefyre-commenting-at-allthingsd/?mod=atd-desktop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt; for switching to LiveFyre from the widely-used Disqus are interesting. Under LiveFyre, users can &amp;ldquo;more readily share comments to Facebook and Twitter&amp;rdquo; which Disqus already did; &amp;ldquo;tag friends and draw them into the stream&amp;rdquo; which increases clutter; and &amp;ldquo;accurately flag other comments as spam or offensive&amp;rdquo; which flat-out doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, if the spam on TechCrunch is any indication. Additionally, they can &amp;ldquo;follow conversations across multiple platforms,&amp;rdquo; which the post doesn&amp;rsquo;t elaborate upon. Does it aggregate social media which links to the parent post, a la Disqus?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it&amp;rsquo;s something much more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comments-from-everywhere&#34;&gt;Comments From Everywhere!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/liveFyreSync.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, LiveFyre implemented a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livefyre.com/comments/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;comment feature&lt;/a&gt; called SocialSync:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Livefyre SocialSync, the conversation happening on Facebook and Twitter automatically syncs directly to your content, where it belongs. SocialSync comments can be replied to and interacted with just like any other comment, including being automatically posted back to Twitter or Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, this feature is enabled for TechCrunch and Mashable.* Let&amp;rsquo;s say a Facebook user comments on one of TechCrunch&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10151659746677952&amp;amp;set=a.114456157951.118433.8062627951&amp;amp;type=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook posts&lt;/a&gt;. Those comments are synchronized to the LiveFyre comments for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2013/05/02/smartphonetographers/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;linked post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those comments become LiveFyre comments. And the Facebook user has no input, nor any notification that their comments are being used this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;socialsync-s-flat-out-lie&#34;&gt;SocialSync&amp;rsquo;s Flat-Out Lie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In LiveFyre&amp;rsquo;s own words, the conversations &amp;ldquo;sync&amp;rdquo; across platforms. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synchronization&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Synchronization&lt;/a&gt; implies a two-way interation, i.e. actions on one platform affect the other. In this example, there are four use cases for the interaction to be called &amp;ldquo;sync&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comments on Facebook should appear on LiveFyre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comments on LiveFyre should appear on Facebook.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replies and Likes on comments on Facebook should appear on the corresponding comment in LiveFyre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replies and Likes on comments on LiveFyre should appear on the corresponding comment in Facebook.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of those four scenarios, only #1 is true, and even more importantly, #2, #3, and #4 are impossible to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LiveFyre doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what your Facebook account is and cannot perform actions on your behalf on Facebook unless you register solely with that account. Therefore, your comments won&amp;rsquo;t sync to the Facebook comment thread if you use any other login type. (the ability to use multiple types of logins being another touted feature of LiveFyre, of course). Likewise, Likes on Facebook Comments can&amp;rsquo;t translate to LiveFyre Likes if the users don&amp;rsquo;t have a LiveFyre account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of connection also breaks notifications of replies. Since there&amp;rsquo;s no way to ensure the two accounts are linked, there&amp;rsquo;s no way to notify a Facebook user when their synced comment on LiveFyre has a reply. This has two effects: a) the Facebook user won&amp;rsquo;t continue the discussion and b) the replier is wasting his time making a comment to a person who likely won&amp;rsquo;t ever read it. Both result in less fruitful discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SocialSync is broken and impossible to fix. Also, the lag from when comments are synced from Facebook to LiveFyre takes about 10-20 minutes, making sync worthless on highly-discussed event blogs posts anyways..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-owns-your-facebook-comments&#34;&gt;Who Owns Your Facebook Comments?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I said that LiveFyre &amp;ldquo;steals&amp;rdquo; Facebook comments in the headline, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t being facetious. It&amp;rsquo;s not obvious that this feature even exists in the first place, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re not a comment addict (I sent a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir/status/311959448694435840&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; to the TechCrunch head editor to confirm that this was intended behavior). How is the typical person supposed to know what their comments are being used for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, your comments on TechCrunch&amp;rsquo;s Facebook wall post that are synced to LiveFyre are Public to everyone, and there is no expectation of privacy. But who owns those comments?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments appear in LiveFyre matching the style and functionality of any other LiveFyre comment, except with a &amp;ldquo;from Facebook&amp;rdquo; designation. For all intents and purposes, it&amp;rsquo;s a LiveFyre comment that you have no controll over. It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that since LiveFyre doesn&amp;rsquo;t know your Facebook account, you can&amp;rsquo;t even delete the syndicated comment in LiveFyre . LiveFyre comments on the post have greater SEO than Facebook comments, so hopefully you don&amp;rsquo;t say anything embarrassing on the Facebook page. LiveFyre is in control of your destiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the benefits to SocialSync anyways, when it barely works? Bigger numbers for the comment count of a post? That&amp;rsquo;s irrelevant when the comments on the Facebook posts are made spur-of-the-moment, and are usually very low quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of sync between isn&amp;rsquo;t terrible in itself. Facebook Comments and the recently announced Google%2B Comment System essentially does sync by blurring the lines between a Google%2B post and a comment, but unlike LiveFyre, the user still retains control over the comment, receives reply notifications, and can delete their comment when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the least, I&amp;rsquo;ve stopped posting on TechCrunch&amp;rsquo;s Facebook page. That&amp;rsquo;s not a good thing for either TechCrunch or LiveFyre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interestingly, SocialSync is not enabled on CNet or AllThingsD&amp;rsquo;s implementations of LiveFyre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>How To Kill The Reader Comments Of A Popular Tech Blog</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2013/01/its-a-metaphor-maybe/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 21:38:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2013/01/its-a-metaphor-maybe/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;In March of 2011, &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2011/03/01/facebook-rolls-out-overhauled-comments-system-try-them-now-on-techcrunch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TechCrunch implemented&lt;/a&gt; the just-announced Facebook Comments functionality on their blog. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://developers.facebook.com/docs/reference/plugins/comments/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook Comments Box&lt;/a&gt; is an official plugin from Facebook which allows users who are logged into Facebook to instantly comment on a blog post or article; no registration needed. Adding a Facebook Comments Box to a website is simple, it provides a visual style that can work with any blog design, and it can have users share their posts on Facebook, which leverages the commenter&amp;rsquo;s friends to drive more traffic to the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first began commenting on TechCrunch in July of the same year, mostly to test out the full functionality of Facebook Comments, after having spent a lot of time experimenting with &lt;a href=&#34;http://disqus.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; and Gawker&amp;rsquo;s custom comment system (I talk about it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/Online-Commenting/Whats-the-deal-with-Max-Woolf-on-TechCrunch-AOL-comments&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). During that time, my comments began to make me rather infamous, both in good ways, and surprisingly bad. (once, a well-respected entrepreneur messaged me saying &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve talked to VCs and they&amp;rsquo;ve said they will never invest in you because of your comments. FYI.&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 2012. Other blogs on the Aol blogging network, such as Engadget, Joystiq, and TechCrunch itself, have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.engadget.com/2012/10/11/engadget-livefyre-commenting-system/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;decided&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joystiq.com/2012/04/04/joystiqs-new-commenting-system-is-live/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;migrate&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livefyre.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LiveFyre&lt;/a&gt;, another blog commenting system which allows readers to comment using their social identities, in addition to a few flashy Web 2.0 features. I figured it was a matter of time until TechCrunch implemented it themselves. And in January 2013, &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/22/we-want-you-back/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;they did&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought I would like the change. Facebook Comments has their own problems that a switch to Livefyre could solve. I was wrong. The stated reasons for the change were &amp;ldquo;we want more comments,&amp;rdquo; but a large amount of low-value comments (and images), with no way to identify good ones, along with the increased hassle of commenting, will end up backfiring. I&amp;rsquo;m honestly afraid that the switch from Facebook Comments could kill quality comments on TechCrunch completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pros-and-cons-of-facebook-comments&#34;&gt;The Pros and Cons of Facebook Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As said earlier, Facebook comments excel in their ease of implementation, light aesthetic, and zero-click registration. More importantly, it lends a lot of credibility to the comments, as they have (usually) been authenticated as a real person. Whenever a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; person likes or comments on your own comment, it is very satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/alexia.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, there are a few unobvious nuances:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For most blog systems, you receive a notification whenever someone replies to your post. In the original implementation of FB Comments, you receive one whenever someone likes or replies to your comment, in the same manner you&amp;rsquo;re notified on a typical Facebook status. This has changed recently: now, you don&amp;rsquo;t receive notification for likes/replies on your comment, and instead you &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;only receive notifications when other people comment on the same post&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out if this is a bug or a feature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is no spam filter.&lt;/strong&gt; As many can attest, Facebook has been terrible at combating spam both on the main website and off. All spam cleaning must be done &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt;, which can be time-consuming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtually no customization for the comments&lt;/strong&gt;. On the administrative side, the only significant options you have for commenting are how many comments appear initially, and the default sort order. It makes sense for Facebook to limit customization to protect their own branding, but it&amp;rsquo;s frustrating for both the admin and readers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commenters do not have access to a list of comments that they&amp;rsquo;ve made.&lt;/strong&gt; This one in particular upset me, which is one of the reasons I&amp;rsquo;ve aggregated all my comments &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/category/blog-comments/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Facebook&amp;rsquo;s count of comments lies. **The count provided by Facebook does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; include replies to comments, unlike every blog comment system since the beginning of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been zero improvements to Facebook Comments since 2011. It&amp;rsquo;s disappointing, but there&amp;rsquo;s not much that can be done&amp;hellip; except considing competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;livefyre-makes-comments-burn&#34;&gt;LiveFyre Makes Comments BURN!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LiveFyre, on a typical blog like this one, has quite a few perks that Facebook Comments does not. It allows users to comment just by linking a social identity, such as Facebook or Twitter. Or you can remain anonymous. You receive notifications by email. Images and video are embedded into posts. Posts appear in real time, increasing the interaction for live events. And, you have a profile which lists all the comments you&amp;rsquo;ve ever made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LiveFyre also has comment editing and an indicator of how many users are viewing the current blog post, but for some reason, the implementation of LiveFyre on TechCrunch disabled these features. Hmm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/comments2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core features good on paper. The problem is with the implementation. &lt;a href=&#34;http://fyre.it/u2jnrP&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;This comment&lt;/a&gt; does a good summary, but here&amp;rsquo;s the gist when compared to Facebook Comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**Anonymous comments are &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; low-quality comments. **With Facebook Comments, rational people will not make stupid comments that are tied with their real name. With anonymous comments, people can troll as much as they want without any repercussions. Yes, with more accessible to comments leads to a higher chance of quality comments by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_large_numbers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;law of large numbers&lt;/a&gt;, but that is completely irrelevant because&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is no way to sort by high-quality comments&lt;/strong&gt;. Facebook Comments, by default, sorts comments by the number of likes that they have received: more likes, the higher up they are in the comment thread. LiveFyre only allows sorting in chronological order and reverse chronological order. No exception. This strongly reduces the &lt;em&gt;motivation&lt;/em&gt; for high-quality posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New comments that are loaded live forcibly scroll down all comments.&lt;/strong&gt; Imagine: you&amp;rsquo;re reading a good comment, and a new comment loads and &lt;em&gt;pushes&lt;/em&gt; the comment away. With spam. You&amp;rsquo;ll become frustrated very quickly. This may not be a concern for blogs with low user-bases, but for popular blogs, this can become irritating very quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Images and video appear in-line, and are very large.&lt;/strong&gt; This makes them more visible, which is a good thing, &lt;em&gt;unless&lt;/em&gt; they&amp;rsquo;re memes and spam. Then it&amp;rsquo;s terrible. And since people can comment anonymously, there&amp;rsquo;s a significant risk factor. Images/video, due to their size, cause comment scrolling even faster!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-impact-of-livefyre-on-techcrunch&#34;&gt;The impact of LiveFyre on TechCrunch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/ToKillACommentsSection.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LiveFyre works on a typical WordPress blog, but when applied to large sites such as Engadget and TechCrunch, whose size attracts trolls, it can be crippling. It&amp;rsquo;s like &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar&#39;s_number&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dunbar&amp;rsquo;s Number&lt;/a&gt; on a macro scale: there&amp;rsquo;s a mathematical limit on the number of people who visit one place on the internet until it degenerates into madness and memes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with the criticisms above, I still prefer Facebook Comments, and I implement it on my own site, as zero-click registration and real name validation is paramount. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely the lesser of two evils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main argument TechCrunch used to justify the switch from Facebook Comments to LiveFyre is that users aren&amp;rsquo;t commenting as much. That&amp;rsquo;s a given, since you can&amp;rsquo;t comment anonymously. It&amp;rsquo;s the old debate of quantity vs. quality: in the case of comments, however, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; in favor of quality. I&amp;rsquo;d rather read a comments section with one or two comments than a comments section consisting of 90% anonymous spammers who make me lose faith in humanity. Losing faith in humanity is not healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll probably be toning down my comments on TechCrunch even moreso. My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/Online-Commenting/Whats-the-deal-with-Max-Woolf-on-TechCrunch-AOL-comments&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;primary motivation for commenting&lt;/a&gt; was, and still is, making people laugh and smile. But if other readers have to dig through anonymous spam just to find my comments, then there&amp;rsquo;s not much point. I could spam my comments to my Facebook profile every time I make one, but that would cause the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; issue.*&lt;br /&gt;
*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize that this is a first-world problem. Even more of a first world problem than &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;auto-downloading pictures of cute puppies&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m not mad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m just sad. :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT (May 2013)&lt;/strong&gt;: When this article was published, this blog was using Facebook Comments, however I switched the comments system to Disqus just to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>