<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thought Piece on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/categories/thought-piece/</link><description>Recent content in Thought Piece on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2018 09:15:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://minimaxir.com/categories/thought-piece/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Things About Real-World Data Science Not Discussed In MOOCs and Thought Pieces</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2018/10/data-science-protips/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2018 09:15:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2018/10/data-science-protips/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data science&lt;/a&gt; has been sweeping the tech world. With a large variety of powerful free open-sourced tools and now the computing power to utilize them to their full potential, data science is more accessible than ever and has become &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-05-18/-sexiest-job-ignites-talent-wars-as-demand-for-data-geeks-soars&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;America&amp;rsquo;s hottest job&lt;/a&gt;. One problem: there&amp;rsquo;s no consensus on &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2018/08/what-data-scientists-really-do-according-to-35-data-scientists&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;what data scientists &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; do&lt;/a&gt; in a professional setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a rise in &lt;em&gt;romantic&lt;/em&gt; thought pieces lately (especially on &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;) about how data scientists are wizards and can solve any problem (with bonus points if it cites AI). If you follow publications like &lt;a href=&#34;https://towardsdatascience.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Towards Data Science&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll notice persistent tropes in the more code-oriented posts: Python is the king programming language for data science, use &lt;a href=&#34;http://scikit-learn.org/stable/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;https://xgboost.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;XGBoost&lt;/a&gt; and logistic regression for predicting categorical variable(s), use &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandas.pydata.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt; for processing tabular data, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nltk.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NLTK&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word2vec&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;word2vec&lt;/a&gt; for processing text data, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tensorflow.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TensorFlow&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;https://keras.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Keras&lt;/a&gt;/convolutional neural networks for processing image data, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-means_clustering&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;-means&lt;/a&gt; for clustering data, split the processed dataset into training and test datasets for model training, tweak hyperparameters/model features &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/1838/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;until results on the test dataset are good&lt;/a&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/data-science-protips/thought.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tropes aren&amp;rsquo;t inappropriate or misleading, but the analysis often doesn&amp;rsquo;t quantify the insight/value of the results. Modeling is just one small part (and often the &lt;em&gt;easiest&lt;/em&gt; part) of a very complex system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data-oriented MOOCs (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Massive Online Open Courses&lt;/a&gt;) like Andrew Ng&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Coursera course on Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://course.fast.ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;fast.ai&amp;rsquo;s course on Deep Learning&lt;/a&gt; are good academic introductions to the theory and terminology behind data science and other related fields. Although MOOCs have many practice problems for prospective data scientists to solve, they don&amp;rsquo;t make you an expert in the field capable of handling messier real-world problems, nor claim to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern data science isn&amp;rsquo;t about burying your head in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://jupyter.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; and staring at the screen watching training loss numbers trickle down (although it&amp;rsquo;s definitely fun!). There&amp;rsquo;s a lot more to it, some of which I&amp;rsquo;ve learned firsthand working as a Data Scientist at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed&lt;/a&gt; for over a year. To borrow a statistical term, MOOCs and thought pieces &lt;em&gt;overfit&lt;/em&gt; to a certain style of data science that is not robust to the vast uncertainties of the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-benefit-tradeoffs-of-data-science&#34;&gt;The Cost/Benefit Tradeoffs of Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data science often follows the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/a&gt;: 80% of the work takes 20% of the effort. Thought pieces demonstrate that you can just toss data indiscriminately into scikit-learn or a deep learning framework and get neat-looking results. The value of a data scientist, however, is when and &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; to further development on a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/competitions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kaggle competitions&lt;/a&gt; are a popular and often-recommended way to get exposure to real-world data science problems. Many teams of statisticians compete to create the best model for a given dataset (where &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; usually means minimizing the predictive loss/error of the model), with prizes for the highest-performing models. Kaggle also encourages clever modeling techniques such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/grid_search.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;grid search&lt;/a&gt; of thousands of model hyperparameter combinations and ensembling disparate models to create a megamodel which results in &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; better predictive performance, but just might give the edge to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are a few important differences between modeling in a Kaggle competition and modeling in a data science team. Kaggle competitions last for &lt;em&gt;weeks&lt;/em&gt; when a professional data scientist may need to spend time on other things. Ensembling gigantic machine learning models makes predictions very slow and the models themselves very large; both of which may cause difficulty deploying them into production (e.g. the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2012/04/netflix-prize-costs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Netflix Prize&lt;/a&gt; movie recommendation models famously &amp;ldquo;did not seem to justify the engineering effort needed to bring them into a production environment&amp;rdquo;). And most importantly, there may not be a significant &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; performance difference between a 1st place Kaggle model that takes days/weeks to optimize and a simple scikit-learn/XGBoost baseline that can be built in a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterintuitively, it may be better to trade performance for speed/memory with a weaker-but-faster model; in business cases, speed and scalability are important implementation constraints. But even with scikit-learn, the model is still a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_box&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;black box&lt;/a&gt; with little idea to the data scientist how the model makes its decisions. One final option is to go back to basics altogether with a &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; linear/logistic regression model, where the predictive performance may be even weaker and the model &lt;a href=&#34;http://statisticsbyjim.com/regression/ols-linear-regression-assumptions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;must follow several statistical assumptions&lt;/a&gt;, but the model feature coefficients and statistical significance &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.minitab.com/blog/adventures-in-statistics-2/how-to-interpret-regression-analysis-results-p-values-and-coefficients&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;are easily interpretable&lt;/a&gt; to explain the importance of each input feature (if any) and make actionable, informed decisions for the business. Being a data scientist requires making educated judgments about these tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-scientists-still-use-business-intelligence-tools&#34;&gt;Data Scientists Still Use Business Intelligence Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hobbyist data scientist without a budget may opt to build their own workflows and data pipelines using free tools. However, professional data scientists have a finite amount of free time (as do all engineers), so there&amp;rsquo;s a massive opportunity cost when reinventing the wheel unnecessarily. Enterprise BI tools such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tableau.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tableau&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://looker.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Looker&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://modeanalytics.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mode Analytics&lt;/a&gt; help retrieve and present data with easy-to-digest dashboards for anyone in the company. They&amp;rsquo;re never cheap, but they&amp;rsquo;re much cheaper to the company than having a data scientist spend valuable time to develop and maintain similar tooling over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a stakeholder wants a data report ASAP, there&amp;rsquo;s no problem falling back to using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SQL&lt;/a&gt; to query a data warehouse and output results into an Excel spreadsheet (plus pretty data visualizations!) to quickly transport in an email. Part of being a data scientist is working out which tools are best appropriate at what time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some might argue that using BI tools and SQL are not responsibilities for data scientists, but instead for Business Analysts or Data Analysts. That&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_true_Scotsman&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;No True Scotsman&lt;/a&gt; way of looking at it; there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of overlap in data science with other analytical fields, and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-scientists-are-software-engineers-too&#34;&gt;Data Scientists Are Software Engineers Too&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although MOOCs encourage &lt;em&gt;self&lt;/em&gt;-study, data science is a collaborative process. And not just with other data scientists on a team, but with other software engineers in the company. Version control tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; are often used for data scientists to upload their portfolio projects publicly to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, but there are many other important features for use in a company-wide collaborative environment such as branching a repository, making pull requests, and merging conflicts. Beyond that are modern development QA practices, such as test environments, consistent code style, and code reviews. The full process varies strongly by company: Airbnb has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/scaling-knowledge-at-airbnb-875d73eff091&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;good thought piece&lt;/a&gt; about how they utilize their Knowledge Base for data science collaboration using Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the very hard and surprisingly underdiscussed aspects of data science is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DevOps&lt;/a&gt;, and how to actually get a statistical model into production. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/resources/what-container&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Docker containers&lt;/a&gt;, for example, are newer technology that&amp;rsquo;s hard to learn, but have many data science and DevOps benefits by mitigating Python dependency hell and ensuring a consistent environment for model deployment and execution. And once the model is in production, data scientists, data engineers, and dedicated DevOps personnel need to work together to figure out if the model has the expected output, if the model is performing with expected speed/memory overhead, how often to retrain the model on fresh data (plus the scheduling/data pipelining necessary to do so), and how to efficiently route predictions out of the system to the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-science-can-t-solve-everything&#34;&gt;Data Science Can&amp;rsquo;t Solve Everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data science experiments (even those utilizing magical AI) are allowed to fail, and not just in the fail-to-reject-the-null-hypothesis sense. Thought pieces typically discuss successful projects, which leads to a survivorship bias. Even with massive amounts of input data, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;likely&lt;/em&gt; for a model to fail to converge and offer zero insight, or an experiment fail to offer statistically significant results (common with &lt;a href=&#34;https://vwo.com/ab-testing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A/B testing&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;real world data science is an R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of 0.10 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/GoogleNext18?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#GoogleNext18&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/qNsno2dscR&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/qNsno2dscR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Max Woolf (@minimaxir) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir/status/1021885939361042432?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty of real-world data science is recognizing if a given problem &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be solved, how much of your valuable time to spend iterating to &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; solve it, how to report to stakeholders if it &lt;em&gt;can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; be solved, and what are the next steps if that&amp;rsquo;s the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/stephaniemlee/brian-wansink-cornell-p-hacking&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;-hack&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-science-and-ethics&#34;&gt;Data Science and Ethics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the rise of the &amp;ldquo;data science/AI is magic!&amp;rdquo; era, massive algorithmic and statistical failures suggest that data science might not always make the world a better place. Amazon built a resume-reading model which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;accidentally learned to be sexist&lt;/a&gt;. Facebook overestimated &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/2018/10/17/17989712/facebook-inaccurate-video-metrics-inflation-lawsuit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;performance metrics on their videos&lt;/a&gt;, causing complete business pivots for media organizations in vain, indirectly &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2018/10/facebook-driven-video-push-may-have-cost-483-journalists-their-jobs/573403/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;leading to hundreds of layoffs&lt;/a&gt;. YouTube&amp;rsquo;s recommended video algorithms &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jamesbridle/something-is-wrong-on-the-internet-c39c471271d2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;drove children towards shocking and disturbing content&lt;/a&gt;. And these companies have some of the best data talent &lt;em&gt;in the entire world&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;qualitative&lt;/em&gt; output of a model or data analysis is just as important as the quantitative performance, if not more. Allowing dangerous model output to hit production and impact &lt;em&gt;millions&lt;/em&gt; of consumers is a failure of QA at all levels. In fairness these companies usually fix these issues, but only &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; journalists &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/10/19/opinion/facebook-twitter-journalism-misinformation.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;point them out&lt;/a&gt;. The problem with blindly chasing a performance metric (like Kaggle) is that it ignores collateral, unexpected effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Don’t be data-driven. Be data-informed. Metrics should never be in charge because they have no moral compass.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kim Goodwin (@kimgoodwin) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kimgoodwin/status/1051849805280948224?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 15, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe recommending shocking videos is what maximizes clickthrough rate or ad revenue per the models according to a business dashboard. Unfortunately, if the data justifies it and the business stakeholders encourage it, the company may &lt;em&gt;accept the consequences&lt;/em&gt; of a flawed algorithm if they don&amp;rsquo;t outweigh the benefits. It&amp;rsquo;s important for data scientists to be aware that they may be party to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize the irony of using a data science thought piece to argue against data science thought pieces. In fairness, some Medium thought pieces do apply data science in very &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; ways or touch on very obscure-but-impactful aspects of frameworks, and I enjoy reading those. The field is still very broadly defined, and your experiences may differ from this post, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re working for a more research-based institution. Unfortunately, I don’t have any new advice for &lt;em&gt;getting&lt;/em&gt; a data science job, which is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir/status/951117788835278848&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;still very difficult&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The popular idea that being a data scientist is a 40-hours-a-week Kaggle competition is &lt;strong&gt;incorrect&lt;/strong&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot more to it that&amp;rsquo;s not as sexy which, in my opinion, is the more interesting aspect of the data science field as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Importance of Sanity-Checking Datasets Before Analysis</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2016/04/trust-but-verify/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2016/04/trust-but-verify/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve done some cool things with movie data using a dataset from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.omdbapi.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;OMDb API&lt;/a&gt;, which is sourced from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IMDb&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rotten Tomatoes&lt;/a&gt; data. In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2016/01/movie-revenue-ratings/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; on the dataset, I plotted the relationship between the domestic box office revenue of movies and their Rotten Tomatoes scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/movie-revenue-ratings/box-office-rating-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to take another look at domestic Box Office Revenues with aggregate statistics such as means/medians on categorical variables such as MPAA rating and release month. For this type of analysis in particular, I&amp;rsquo;ll also need to implement code in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; for inflation adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I ran into a few unexpectedly silly issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seeing-double&#34;&gt;Seeing Double&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many similarities between data validation and the Quality Assurance process of product development, which is why this particular area appeals to me personally as a Software QA Engineer. Whenever a cool dataset is released publicly, I play around with it to look for any obvious flaws and to get a good all-around benchmark on the robustness of the data (this is a separate procedure from the traditional &amp;ldquo;data cleaning&amp;rdquo; phase necessary to begin quantification on some poorly-structured datasets).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the extreme values in the data make sense? Is the data encoded in a sane format? Are there any obvious gaps or logical contradictions in summary representations of the data, especially when compared to other canonical sources?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These concerns are also some of the reasons I&amp;rsquo;ve switched to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://jupyter.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; as my primary data science IDE. After each block of code which transforms data, I can print the data frame inline to immediately see the results of the code execution, and refer back to them if anything odd happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say I have a data frame of Movies using the latest data dump (3/26/16) from OMDb. This data set contains 1,160,273 movies, including both IMDb and Rotten Tomatoes data. After cleaning the data (not shown), I can use the R package &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt; by Hadley Wickham to sort the data frame by Box Office Revenue descending, and print the &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt; (top) of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-R&#34;&gt;print(df %&amp;gt;% select(imdbID, Title, Year, BoxOffice) %&amp;gt;% arrange(desc(BoxOffice)) %&amp;gt;% head(25), n = 25)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/trust-but-verify/data-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those movies being the best &lt;em&gt;makes sense&lt;/em&gt;. For &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/star_wars_episode_vii_the_force_awakens/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Star Wars: The Force Awakens&lt;/a&gt;, I can compare it to the Box Office reported on the corresponding Rotten Tomatoes page, which in turn matches the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=starwars7.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;domestic Box Office Revenue&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boxofficemojo.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Box Office Mojo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Knight_%28film%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Dark Knight&lt;/a&gt; appears &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt;? How?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no way I would have missed something this obvious during the sanity-check for my previous article. In order to make sure that I&amp;rsquo;m not going insane, I double-checked the December 2015 data dump I used for that post, derived the top movies with the same methodology for the modern data dump, and the duplicate movies &lt;em&gt;were not present&lt;/em&gt;. Weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 2 different IDs for
The Dark Knight, and for some other movies near the top (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4817264/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Inside Out&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3138972/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Gravity&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;). Fortunately, duplicate data like this is easy to debug. The second data entry for The Dark Knight has a greater IMDb ID (1774602) which means it was likely added to the site later. Let&amp;rsquo;s look up the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1774602/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;corresponding IMDb page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/trust-but-verify/dark-knight.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huh. Apparently someone put a filler movie entry with the same name and release year as a blockbuster movie in hopes that people search for it by accident (and since it received 50 ratings and an average score of 8.6, this tactic was successful).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the Rotten Tomatoes &lt;a href=&#34;http://developer.rottentomatoes.com/docs/read/json/v10/Movie_Alias&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IMDb Lookup API&lt;/a&gt;, we find that &amp;ldquo;The Dark Knight&amp;rdquo; page on Rotten Tomatoes&amp;hellip;&lt;a href=&#34;http://api.rottentomatoes.com/api/public/v1.0/movie_alias.json?type=imdb&amp;amp;id=1774602&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can run a safe deduplicate by removing entries with the same title (excluding the &amp;ldquo;The&amp;rdquo; if present) and release year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-R&#34;&gt;df_dup &amp;lt;- df %&amp;gt;% select(Title, Year) %&amp;gt;% mutate(Title = gsub(&amp;quot;The &amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&amp;quot;, Title))
dup &amp;lt;- duplicated(df_dup) # find entry indices which are duplicates
rm(df_dup) # remove temp dataframe
df_dedup &amp;lt;- df %&amp;gt;% filter(!dup) # keep entries which are *not* dups
print(df_dedup %&amp;gt;% select(imdbID, Title, Year, BoxOffice) %&amp;gt;% arrange(desc(BoxOffice)) %&amp;gt;% head(25), n = 25)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/trust-but-verify/data-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There we go! The de-duped dataset has 1,114,431 movies, impliying that there were 45,842 of these duplicate entries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure &lt;em&gt;whose&lt;/em&gt; fault it is that duplicate movies suddenly became present in the data dump: OMDb or Rotten Tomatoes. &lt;em&gt;But it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter&lt;/em&gt;: the wrong entries still need to be addressed, and it&amp;rsquo;s good to have a test case for the future too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;inflation-station&#34;&gt;Inflation Station&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/a/26068058&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Stack Overflow answer&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/users/1048757/brash-equilibrium&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ben Hanowell&lt;/a&gt; has a good R implementation and rationale for implementing inflation adjustment using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/CPIAUCSL.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;historical Consumer Price Index data&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stlouisfed.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the index for each year (averaging each month for simplicity) and create an adjustment factor to convert historical dollar amounts into present-day dollar amounts. Much better than plugging hundreds of thousands of values into an online calculator. Here&amp;rsquo;s the SO code made &lt;code&gt;dplyr&lt;/code&gt;-friendly for this purpose, with the requisite sanity-checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-R&#34;&gt;inflation &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/CPIAUCSL.csv&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
group_by(Year = as.integer(substr(DATE, 1, 4))) %&amp;gt;%
summarize(Avg_Value = mean(VALUE)) %&amp;gt;% # average across all months
mutate(Adjust = tail(Avg_Value, 1) / Avg_Value) # normalize by most-recent year
print(inflation %&amp;gt;% head())
print(inflation %&amp;gt;% tail())
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/trust-but-verify/inf.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, to get the inflation-adjusted Box Office Revenue for a movie released in 1949 in 2016 dollars, we multiply the reported revenue by 10. That sounds about right (and matches closely enough to the output of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.bls.gov/cgi-bin/cpicalc.pl?cost1=1&amp;amp;year1=1949&amp;amp;year2=2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bureau of Labor Statistics inflation calculator&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now map each inflation adjustment factor to each movie by merging the two datasets (on the &lt;code&gt;Year&lt;/code&gt; column), then multiply the Box Office revenue by the adjustment factor to get the inflation-adjusted revenue. Plus another sanity-check for good measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;df_dedup_join &amp;lt;- df_dedup %&amp;gt;% inner_join(inflation) %&amp;gt;% mutate(AdjBoxOffice = BoxOffice * Adjust)
print(df_dedup_join %&amp;gt;% select(Title, Year, AdjBoxOffice) %&amp;gt;% arrange(desc(AdjBoxOffice)) %&amp;gt;% head(25), n=25)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/trust-but-verify/data-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh-oh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lorax_(TV_special)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Lorax&lt;/a&gt; probably earned $1.2 billion in VHS sales for Earth Day education &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt;, but the TV special was never released in theaters. There was a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lorax_(film)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CGI remake of The Lorax&lt;/a&gt; a few years ago which was reasonably popular. Could it be that someone at Rotten Tomatoes or Box Office Mojo confused the two media?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is exactly what happened. On Rotten Tomatoes, The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the-lorax/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1972 Lorax&lt;/a&gt; was encoded with similar box office revenue as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_lorax/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2012 Lorax&lt;/a&gt;; then the inflation factor sextupled it. For this type of data fidelity issue, it&amp;rsquo;s considerably more obvious whose at fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that&amp;rsquo;s not the end of problems with the dataset. I compared my results with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vox.com/2016/4/4/11351788/batman-v-superman-terrible-reviews#undefined&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Vox&amp;rsquo;s dataset&lt;/a&gt; on worldwide historical box office revenues. In the Top 200 Movies by inflation-adjusted revenue, there are noted historical movie omissions such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/jaws/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jaws&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/star_wars/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Star Wars: A New Hope&lt;/a&gt;. It turns out Rotten Tomatoes does not have Box Office Revenue data for these movies at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a very serious problem which I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about if it blocks any analysis on aggregate box office data completely. In the end, sanity-checking third party data is important because you never know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the data will surprise you, until it&amp;rsquo;s too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view the Top 200 movies by domestic box office revenue for each of the &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;15&lt;/sub&gt; source dataset, the &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt; dataset, the &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt; deduped dataset, and the &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt; deduced inflation-adjusted data &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/movie-data-sanity-checking&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;, along with the Jupyter notebook.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Facebook Reactions and the Problems With Quantifying Likes Differently</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2016/02/facebook-reactions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2016/02/facebook-reactions/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Facebook added &lt;a href=&#34;http://newsroom.fb.com/news/2016/02/reactions-now-available-globally/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook Reactions&lt;/a&gt;, allowing users to do more than just &amp;ldquo;Like&amp;rdquo; posts and statuses as they have done for the past decade. Likes were the universal symbol of approval on social media. Now, Facebook users can apply more granular responses, from positive emotions like &lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt;, to negative emotions such as &lt;strong&gt;Angry&lt;/strong&gt;. This was widely believed to be Facebook&amp;rsquo;s compromise instead of adding a Dislike button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/facebook_react.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there&amp;rsquo;s an ulterior motive. The use of reactions provides organic data on the sentiment of a status, which is helpful for numerous marketing and statistical applications. As &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/alexkantrowitz/facebook-reactions-launch-today&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed notes&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook ads may be able &amp;ldquo;to write one product message for someone who mostly uses &lt;strong&gt;Sad&lt;/strong&gt; and another who mostly uses &lt;strong&gt;Wow&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Love.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time a big social network has tried implementing reactions alongside Likes/Dislikes. Four years ago, YouTube added &lt;a href=&#34;http://googlesystem.blogspot.com/2011/06/youtube-reactions.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reaction buttons&lt;/a&gt; to their comments section:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/youtube-reactions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and removed them sometime after without fanfare, replacing it with the simple Like/Dislike bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presumably, YouTube implemented the buttons for the similar reason as Facebook. What makes things different now, if anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-quantitative-approach-to-feeling&#34;&gt;A Quantitative Approach to Feeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after YouTube&amp;rsquo;s failure, another data-driven website implemented reaction buttons: BuzzFeed (who else?). At the end of each article (in most categories), registered users can select a quirky reaction to indicate how they felt about the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/buzzfeedreactions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart represents &lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt; internally and is by-far the most-used reaction on BuzzFeed posts. When I started scraping BuzzFeed data in 2014 &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2015/01/linkbait/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;to analyze clickbait&lt;/a&gt;, I made sure to grab the reaction data of other reactions as well to see if there are any interesting trends or correlations between reactions. A cursory glance at the scraped reaction data revealed a problem that forced me to disregard it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important part of variable selection for analysis and modeling is avoiding &lt;em&gt;redundant&lt;/em&gt; features, as that can cause issues such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multicollinearity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;multicollinearity&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overfitting&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;overfitting&lt;/a&gt;. For Facebook, avoiding adding redundant Reactions was an &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/facebook-design/reactions-not-everything-in-life-is-likable-5c403de72a3f&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;explicit design goal&lt;/a&gt; of the feature, but the positive emotions such as &lt;strong&gt;Like&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Wow&lt;/strong&gt; might be overly similar regardless (I believe it fair to compare the behavior of BuzzFeed users with the average Facebook user, given that they hit the same demographics). Do BuzzFeed readers use specific positive reactions differently? Did they use specific negative reactions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rechecked my 2014 data in light of Facebook Reactions. The scraped dataset contains reaction data from 9,883 BuzzFeed articles in the Celebrity, Animals, Books, Longform, and Business categories. From that, I made a &lt;a href=&#34;http://vita.had.co.nz/papers/gpp.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pairs plot&lt;/a&gt; for the counts of all the &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; reactions on the articles to illustrate all bivariate relationships:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lower half of the pairs plot is a scatterplot for the two reactions; the axes represent the number of votes for a given reaction on a BuzzFeed article (both axes are scaled logarithmically), color intensity indicates the number of articles at that X/Y combo, and the line is a linear trendline of least-squares.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The diagonal of the pairs plot represents the density distribution of reaction vote counts for that reaction. (also logarithmically scaled on the X axis)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The upper half of the pairs plot illustrates the Pearson correlation between the non-log quantities of the two reaction variables. The stars represent statistical significance of the correlation test; since the data set is large, all correlations are statistically significant (rejection of null hypothesis of no correlation) at p &amp;lt; 0.001.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/buzzfeed-pos.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the bivariate correlations of positive reactions are &lt;em&gt;moderately or strongly positively correlated&lt;/em&gt;, which is problematic for analysis (except one: apparently, there is little statistical relationship between things that are cute and things that make you go YAAASS). So why not just use the &lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt; reaction, since articles tend to get about 100 Loves, while other reactions get around 10?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the same hold for negative reactions? Relatedly, we would also expect a negative correlation between the number of &lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt; reactions and negative reactions, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/buzzfeed-neg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All negative reactions are positively correlated, as expected, but there is a weak &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; correlation between &lt;strong&gt;Love&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Hate&lt;/strong&gt;, which is definitely not right. There isn&amp;rsquo;t an ideal &amp;ldquo;negative&amp;rdquo; reaction, since all have similar distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does Facebook have 6 different responses to gauge positivity or negativity when one reaction for each would be both more accurate and more intuitive for the user?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conceal-don-t-feel&#34;&gt;Conceal, Don&amp;rsquo;t Feel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other qualitative issues with Facebook&amp;rsquo;s current implementation of Reactions. Apparently, Likes and Reactions are treated &lt;em&gt;differently internally&lt;/em&gt;. As a result, you get separate notifications for Likes and Reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/facebook_react2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? No idea. There is enough Notification spam on Facebook, I don&amp;rsquo;t need &lt;em&gt;double notifications&lt;/em&gt; in my Notification feed for every status I make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s important to note is that a user cannot both Like and React to a status; only one or the other. As a result, the number of Likes on statuses overall will drop, and this is a &lt;em&gt;major&lt;/em&gt; problem for businesses who are dependent on measuring the number of Likes for engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a look at the Facebook Graph API endpoint for &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/graph-api/reference/v2.5/post&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook Page Posts&lt;/a&gt; (same endpoint I use for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-page-post-scraper&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook Page Data Scraper&lt;/a&gt;), and I can confirm that the API can only report the number of Likes on a status; not the number of Likes + Reactions, or number of Likes + number of each Reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebook-reactions/cnn_fb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no way currently to automate the retrieval of Reactions data from Facebook posts, which is an unfortunate oversight (especially considering how Twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.twitter.com/2015/hearts-for-developers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;handled the transition&lt;/a&gt; from Favorites to Likes easily).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/cnn/posts/10154506885211509&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CNN story&lt;/a&gt; I used for that screenshot is anecdotally one of the very few examples I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed where the number of Likes is &lt;em&gt;almost equal&lt;/em&gt; to negative emotions, a relationship which should be weakly correlated and therefore this knowledge may be useful to isolate the story as unusual (and serve ads accordingly). At Facebook&amp;rsquo;s immense scale, identifying a relatively small proportion of unusual stories might be enough to justify adding Reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe this feature is just the harbinger of a new generation of emotionally-charged linkbait. Perhaps there is more to this Facebook Reactions data than what meets the eye, and I&amp;rsquo;ll update my scripts and do further statistical analysis when able. But given what has happened with Reactions data before with YouTube, I am unconvinced and I still believe the functionality as a whole is a usability regression that won&amp;rsquo;t last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Dislike button would have been better, just saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view the code and data used to generate the BuzzFeed Reaction data visualizations &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-reactions/blob/master/buzzfeed_reactions.ipynb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in this Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-reactions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;open-sourced on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, or you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-reactions/raw/master/reactions_pdf.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;view as a PDF&lt;/a&gt;, which is better if you are on a mobile device.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Friends Of My Friends Are Not My Friends</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/01/farcical-friends-of-friends-folly/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/01/farcical-friends-of-friends-folly/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jelly.co/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jelly&lt;/a&gt;, a highly-anticipated social networking app by Twitter co-founder Biz Stone, was released last week. One of Jelly&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.jelly.co/post/72563498393/introducing-jelly&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;underlying principles&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;it’s not hard to imagine that the true promise of a connected society is people helping each other.&amp;rdquo; While using Jelly over the past few days, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people ask whether or not to exercise, make unsubtle plugs for their product, sell a car Craigslist-style, and get amnesia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/jellyposts2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, what? How are these questions representative of &amp;ldquo;a connected society,&amp;rdquo; especially since I don&amp;rsquo;t know any of the question authors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jelly tells its users that they can &amp;ldquo;help friends, or friends-of-friends with their questions.&amp;rdquo; The vast majority of the questions I&amp;rsquo;ve seen are from Friends of Friends. I&amp;rsquo;m Facebook Friends with people who have &lt;strong&gt;thousands&lt;/strong&gt; of friends; the probability that I have something in common with those second-degree friends is low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Websites like Jelly and even Facebook are now utilizing the content made by second-degree &amp;ldquo;friends.&amp;rdquo; Why am I seeing pictures and statuses from friends of friends, who are essentially complete strangers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook-s-farcical-friends-of-friends-folly&#34;&gt;Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Farcical Friends of Friends Folly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple months ago, Facebook again tweaked the News Feed algorithm such that all new Posts on a friend&amp;rsquo;s Wall are shown on your News Feed, even if the person making the Post is a complete stranger to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, Facebook showed posts in your News Feed that were posted on a Friend&amp;rsquo;s wall only if they were made by another Friend. If you are friends with both people, there&amp;rsquo;s likely a common link between all three of you, such as going to the same college or working at the same company. That can make the Wall post more relevant to your interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, people have many social circles. What happens when a stranger not in any of my social circles posts on a Friend&amp;rsquo;s wall?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post recently appeared in my News Feed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/fb-stranger-wall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know who the person with &amp;ldquo;1 mutual friend&amp;rdquo; is. (the &amp;ldquo;1 mutual friend&amp;rdquo; being the friend who received the post). I don&amp;rsquo;t live in Arizona. Why am I seeing this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I may be Facebook Friends with someone, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean I should be Friends with their Friends. Facebook is showing me Posts that aren&amp;rsquo;t relevant to me at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This behavior also extends to your Friends&amp;rsquo; birthday: all &amp;ldquo;Happy Birthday!&amp;rdquo; posts on your Friend&amp;rsquo;s Wall also display in your News Feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This entry was visible on my News Feed for an entire day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/mutual-friends-birthday.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; wants you to wish your Friends happy birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t need to see strangers with &amp;ldquo;1 mutual friend&amp;rdquo; wish my friends Happy Birthday. It&amp;rsquo;s just extra clutter on an already cluttered News Feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, other websites such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; push second-degree friends. Twitter&amp;rsquo;s new &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/i/discover&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Discover&lt;/a&gt; feature highlights users who the people you Follow are themselves Following. LinkedIn shows your connections&amp;rsquo; new connections so you can form connections with them too. But the difference between Twitter/LinkedIn and Facebook/Jelly is that both Facebook and Jelly push the power of &lt;strong&gt;intimate&lt;/strong&gt; friendships, and imposing a sense of intimacy between strangers feels fake and intrudes on actual friendships.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Facebook Hashtags Are Fundamentally Broken</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;This week, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; added &lt;a href=&#34;http://newsroom.fb.com/News/633/Public-Conversations-on-Facebook&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;searchable hashtags&lt;/a&gt; to all status updates and user comments. As with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, whenever a Facebook user posts an status with a #hashtag, that hashtag becomes clickable and leads to a News Feed of all other publically-visible posts with that hashtag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implementation of hashtags in Facebook is an obvious move. Advertisements and television shows display hashtags all the time to encourage users to Tweet about them: it&amp;rsquo;s free marketing, after all. Facebook can piggy-back off those already-existing hashtags and grow user adoption &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; quickly, especially with Facebook-owned &lt;a href=&#34;http://instagram.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt; already supporting hashtags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Facebook is a fundamentally different social network than Twitter. While Twitter uses hashtags to quickly categorize a feed of 140-character thoughts, Facebook&amp;rsquo;s content feeds typically consist of long posts and large images. Additionally, while posts on Twitter are explicitly public or private, Facebook&amp;rsquo;s privacy settings are more granular: if users don&amp;rsquo;t make their posts Public, the hashtag is essentially useless. And the brands are going to &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; hashtags. Maybe too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic of Facebook is flat-out incompatible with the magic of hashtags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-long-didn-t-read&#34;&gt;Too Long; Didn&amp;rsquo;t Read&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/facebooktwitter.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Twitter posts have a length limit, they&amp;rsquo;re short and occupy a consistent amount of space on the webpage. Facebook posts can be near-unlimited length, utilize a large amount of a white space between posts, and also potentially contain an equally-long comment section. As a result, 5 Twitter posts can use the same amount of screen real-estate as 2 Facebook posts. Given the already incredibly low signal-to-noise quality ratio of #hashtag feeds (as evident above), this makes reading hashtag feeds on Facebook a chore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-thousand-words-takes-a-lot-of-space&#34;&gt;A Thousand Words Takes A Lot Of Space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/bieber-twitter.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook displays pictures embedded in posts natively in the feed, while Twitter requires the user to click the Tweet to see the photo. In this case, the ratio of Twitter:Facebook posts can be even worse, in this case 6 Twitter posts for 1 Facebook post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;if-a-hashtag-isn-t-seen-was-it-posted&#34;&gt;If A Hashtag Isn&amp;rsquo;t Seen, Was It Posted?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is opt-in private posting. Facebook is opt-&lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; private posting. That&amp;rsquo;s a big usability problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Facebook hashtag feeds only show posts that are explicitly made Public (or posts from your Friends which are set to a privacy of Friends Only). If the user is unaware that their posts are not Public by default, then their posts containing the hashtag will never be seen and the user won&amp;rsquo;t be able to participate in social hashtag feeds. Although Facebook has made improvements in helping users set the intended privacy level of a post, it makes the process of posting much more deliberate and much less impulsive than Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;brand-branding-marketing-yolo-swag&#34;&gt;#brand #branding #marketing #yolo #swag&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hashtagabuse.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brands love hashtags. The more hashtags included in a Tweet, the more exposure the Tweet receives, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Twitter, there&amp;rsquo;s a limit on the number of hashtags in a Tweet due to the delicate balance between the number of hashtags, the length of the hashtags, and the length of the Tweet itself. On Facebook, you can include &lt;strong&gt;25&lt;/strong&gt; hashtags in any post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there&amp;rsquo;s no consequence for abusing hashtags, expect to see more Facebook brands taking advantage this new free source of marketing. Expect to see Facebook get much more cluttered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;explicit-image-bombing&#34;&gt;Explicit Image Bombing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A malicious user could theoretically insert shock images into popular hashtag feeds. During my testing of Facebook hashtags, there was a surprising amount of nudity in the seemingly-innocuous #many hashtag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Twitter, the volume of Tweets is much higher and the images are hidden by default, so the odds of such an attack working on Facebook are much higher than on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comment-hashtags-different-from-post-hashtags&#34;&gt;Comment Hashtags Different From Post Hashtags&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can hashtag comments on Facebook posts like you can hashtag Facebook posts themselves. But hashtagged comments won&amp;rsquo;t appear in the hashtag News Feed. Whereas on Twitter, Replies are also Tweets and can be hashtagged accordingly. This behavior isn&amp;rsquo;t surprising, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a big inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will Facebook Hashtags fail due to the massive differences between Facebook and Twitter? It&amp;rsquo;s hard to say, but I&amp;rsquo;m skeptical that Facebook will be able to capture the hashtag magic.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>