<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>BuzzFeed on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>/tags/buzzfeed/</link><description>Recent content in BuzzFeed on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 08:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/buzzfeed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Quantifying the Clickbait and Linkbait in BuzzFeed Article Titles</title><link>/2015/01/linkbait/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/01/linkbait/</guid><description>
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;em&gt;UPDATE&lt;/em&gt;: I became a data scientist at BuzzFeed in August 2017. My thoughts about BF have changed significantly in the years since this was published in 2015!
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most significant sources of journalistic content on the entire internet. Of course, that depends on your definition of &amp;ldquo;journalistic&amp;rdquo;: BuzzFeed is one of the first organizations to leverage both social media and the power of language as an editorial business model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed_fb.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BuzzFeed has popularized the use of the &amp;ldquo;listicle&amp;rdquo; as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/lyapalater/group-projects-should-be-wiped-off-the-face-o&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;seen above&lt;/a&gt;: a bulleted list of text blurbs and/or photos that fits the length and depth of a normal blog article. Additionally, BuzzFeed was one of the first news sources to use non-neutral headlines that deliberately invoke a reaction in the reader which then subsequently tempts them to click on the article in an attempt to promote virality. These &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clickbait&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;clickbait&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mashable.com/2013/07/12/linkbait-content-marketing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;linkbait&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; techniques have been responsible for BuzzFeed receiving &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/11/technology/a-move-to-go-beyond-lists-for-content-at-buzzfeed.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;$50 million in venture capital&lt;/a&gt;, and has spawned entire startups and job positions designed solely to emulate BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to determine which phrases in BuzzFeed headlines are the most successful in order to see if it&amp;rsquo;s possible to reverse-engineer BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s business model. Therefore, I scraped BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s website (&lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/buzzscrape/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;after initial frustration&lt;/a&gt;) and obtained 60,378 distinct articles and the corresponding number of Facebook Shares for each article. From there, I decomposed each headline into its &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N-gram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;component n-grams&lt;/a&gt;, allowing me to perform quantitative analysis for each possible permutation of words in the article titles. You probably don&amp;rsquo;t know that the 3 most interesting things I found will blow your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-rise-of-the-listicle&#34;&gt;The Rise of the Listicle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed_listicle.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listicles almost always begin with a numeral as the first or second word. Out of the 60,378 articles I obtained, 26% of them (15,656 articles) are listicles. BuzzFeed clearly believes they are successful, as the proportion of listicles to normal articles has increased over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed-listicle-proportions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listicles can be of any size. The distibution of listicle sizes is centered at the median of 19 entries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed-listicle-histogram.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, there is a positive correlation between listicle size and the number of Facebook shares it receives: A 30-size listicle receives many-multiples of shares more than 10-size listicles. (note the logarithmic scale for FB Shares)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed-listicle-scatterplot.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BuzzFeed has many different types of listicles to appeal to a wide crowd, including &lt;em&gt;[X] reasons&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;[X] books&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;[X] movies&lt;/em&gt;, etc, where &lt;em&gt;[X]&lt;/em&gt; is any 1 or 2-digit numeral. However, BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s go-to listicle phrase has changed over the years. Here are the most-used listicle phrases for each month since 2012:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&#34;width: 100%; max-width: 450px; height: 300px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1U9SWJsmepYdb6YjWCFzM0gsuuDC5PBeFJZkTmJ568fs/pubhtml?gid=1424838564&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012 and 2013, BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s listicles began with &lt;em&gt;the [X]&lt;/em&gt;; in 2014, BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s most-used listicles began with &lt;em&gt;[X] things&lt;/em&gt;. The &amp;ldquo;the&amp;rdquo; is technically redundant; perhaps BuzzFeed decided to make the listicle schema cleaner and &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; formal. It may be possible that &lt;em&gt;[X] things&lt;/em&gt; performs better on average than &lt;em&gt;the [X]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which types of listicles are the most successful on Facebook? Which types of listicles receive the most amount of Facebook shares?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a chart of of the Top 30 types of listicles by the number of Facebook shares those articles have received on average (with a minimum of 50 articles of that listicle type):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed-shares-listicles.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few notes on the chart: the gray bars on each average bar represent a &lt;strong&gt;95% confidence interval&lt;/strong&gt; for the true value of each average, where the confidence interval is obtained through 10,000 iterations of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bootstrapping_%28statistics%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bootstrap resampling&lt;/a&gt;. The dashed vertical line represents the &lt;strong&gt;population average&lt;/strong&gt; of all distinct BuzzFeed articles, at 6,657 Facebook shares, and helps visualize the relative impact of having these words in the title compared to a normal BuzzFeed article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most-posted listicle types mentioned above are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the types of listicles are most shared, however &lt;em&gt;[X] things&lt;/em&gt; does indeed perform slightly better than &lt;em&gt;the [X]&lt;/em&gt; on average. Emotional words, such as &lt;em&gt;insanely&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt;, which you would never see in a more serious journalistic publication, are some of the key drivers of shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look into these keywords more to see if there are any other trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-keywords&#34;&gt;Key Keywords&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed_1gram.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specific keywords may be more informative. Here&amp;rsquo;s the most popular keywords over time, ignoring common &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_words&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;stop words&lt;/a&gt; and listicle words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&#34;width: 100%; max-width: 450px; height: 300px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1U9SWJsmepYdb6YjWCFzM0gsuuDC5PBeFJZkTmJ568fs/pubhtml?gid=1106341985&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most journalistic news sources, BuzzFeed tends to write more frequently toward then-current events. 2012 for example had many articles about the 2012 election, while April 2013 consisted of many articles about the Boston Marathon bombings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which keywords encouraged the most Facebook shares on average?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed-shares-1gram.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a more uncertainty in the accuracy of the average on keywords, especially with the #1 word, &lt;em&gt;career&lt;/em&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s a strong focus on nostalgia, with &lt;em&gt;toys&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;childhood&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;80s&lt;/em&gt;. Certain brands (&lt;em&gt;potter&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;disney&lt;/em&gt;) fit the nostalgia too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High words with a relatively small confidence interval and &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;character&lt;/em&gt;. These are likely caused by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/quizzes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s quizzes&lt;/a&gt;, which have been incredibly popular. Analyzing full phrases is necessary to get a bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-word-phrases&#34;&gt;3-Word Phrases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed_3gram.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After careful analysis, I found that 3-word phrases (trigrams) provided more helpful information than phrases of other lengths. Over time, there are similarities with the popular phrases; they both relate to then-current event and occasionally contain listicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&#34;width: 100%; max-width: 450px; height: 300px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1U9SWJsmepYdb6YjWCFzM0gsuuDC5PBeFJZkTmJ568fs/pubhtml?gid=249061324&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average shares of articles based on phrases in their titles, however, tell the full story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/linkbait/buzzfeed-shares-3gram-v2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can clearly see some the infamous phrases traditionally associated with clickbait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, &lt;em&gt;character are you&lt;/em&gt;, a frequent phrase in quizzes, is what leads to the most virality. (It&amp;rsquo;s worth nothing that these perform 3-4 times better than the best listicles on average). Likewise, you may notice a few phrases are redundant and subset of a bigger phrase (e.g. &lt;em&gt;things you probably&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;you probably don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;probably don&amp;rsquo;t know&lt;/em&gt;), but since the averages FB shares aren&amp;rsquo;t identical, it&amp;rsquo;s not a perfect subset, and therefore the average is relevant. There&amp;rsquo;s also a frequent appeal to &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, the reader, with &lt;em&gt;you/your/you&amp;rsquo;re&lt;/em&gt; appearing in about half of the top phrases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does clickbait work? Of course it does. Granted, there has been a lot of disenchantment with the rise of clickbait; that&amp;rsquo;s why the parody Twitter account &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SavedYouAClick&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@SavedYouAClick&lt;/a&gt; was created and hit 182K followers in months. It&amp;rsquo;s also the reason why &lt;a href=&#34;http://newsroom.fb.com/news/2014/08/news-feed-fyi-click-baiting/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook will now be punishing clickbait&lt;/a&gt; and making them less public in a user&amp;rsquo;s news feed, which will definitely hurt BuzzFeed. That&amp;rsquo;s likely one of the reasons why they are pivoting to quizzes and video content instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t expect clickbait to disappear anytime soon; it&amp;rsquo;s easy and provides a good return-on-investment, both of which are important to scrappy websites trying to market on social media. Or things could come full-circle and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/tomphillips/photos-that-prove-game-of-thrones-happened-in-real-life&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed could publish clickbait about making the best clickbait&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view and download all the BuzzFeed article data and metadata &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1WSx45rT4jZfysmZfzJtjaPO7AxW4XMaJYaCUd5HB2ns/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in this Google Sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All graphics were generated using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-project.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. The charts were created using &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; and the word clouds were created using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/wordcloud/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;wordcloud&lt;/a&gt; package.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Least Effective Method For Blocking Web Scraping of a Website</title><link>/2014/09/buzzscrape/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/09/buzzscrape/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;As someone who typically plays around with data from public website APIs, I figured it would be worthwhile to learn how to get data from websites the old-fashioned way: through force, via web scraping. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_scraping&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Web scraping&lt;/a&gt; is a technique where the user downloads the raw HTML of a webpage, and parses the inherent structure of the webpage to extract the necessary data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to understand the mechanics behind web scraping, I used a tool from new Y Combinator startup &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kimonolabs.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kimono Labs&lt;/a&gt;, which allows the user to click structured elements of any website and quickly create an API that can access all the collected data and convert it into an easy-to-access form. My first target was BuzzFeed, since their social interaction data might be useful in determining how it became so big so quickly, and maybe also determine just how effective those stupid listicles are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;live-free-and-scrape-hard&#34;&gt;Live Free and Scrape Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, here&amp;rsquo;s a pair of typical BuzzFeed articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_example.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the corresponding output of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kimonolabs.com/apis/1x3l57k0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my Kimono Labs BuzzFeed scraper&lt;/a&gt; for those two articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;: {
&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Stop Tweeting Instagram Links&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;href&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;http://www.buzzfeed.com/katienotopoulos/stop-tweeting-instagram-links&amp;quot;
},
&amp;quot;content&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;I CANNOT REMAIN SILENT ON THIS ISSUE ANY LONGER.&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;author&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Katie Notopoulos&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;num_responses&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;123&amp;quot;
},
{
&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;: {
&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;28 Things Your Gchat Availability Status Really Means&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;href&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;http://www.buzzfeed.com/katieheaney/28-things-your-gchat-availability-status-really-means&amp;quot;
},
&amp;quot;content&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Let’s chat.&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;author&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Katie Heaney&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;num_responses&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;13&amp;quot;
}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data format (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;) can be processed and manipulated by nearly any modern programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each BuzzFeed category page has about 22 articles, but the scraper can also access successive pages to retrieve more articles. This works by finding the URL of the next page by deriving the URL from the &amp;ldquo;Older&amp;rdquo; button if present on that page. Then the scraper can find the Older button on the page after that, and so forth, until all pages on BuzzFeed are scraped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_page.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My BuzzFeed scraper, for some reason, only retrieved 10 pages maximum. So I used my QA skills and traced the exact route the scraper took, navigating through all 10 pages by clicking the Older button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was on Page #10 shocked me. OMG. I could not believe my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_disable.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-scrape-for-you&#34;&gt;No Scrape For You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Older button is &lt;em&gt;disabled&lt;/em&gt; on page 10? &lt;strong&gt;WHY?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BuzzFeed is a website created in the 21st century that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/11/technology/a-move-to-go-beyond-lists-for-content-at-buzzfeed.html?_r=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;just raised $50 million&lt;/a&gt;. This is not a peculiar technical limitation due to bad coding or bad infrastructure; this is a deliberate functional aspect of the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my personal mantra that if a startup has a particularly unintuitive UI/UX behavior, it&amp;rsquo;s a form of &amp;ldquo;growth hacking&amp;rdquo; that my feeble brain cannot comprehend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could the reason that BuzzFeed disables access to pages past 10 is that they want to prevent archive browsing, thereby putting more of an emphasis on more recent and more potentially-viral articles? That wouldn&amp;rsquo;t make sense; if a person is so hooked on BuzzFeed articles that they are at Page 10, why stop them? It&amp;rsquo;s still free page views and ad revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s likely that BuzzFeed has statistics on how many users actually visit article pages up to Page 10. Perhaps their data analysts noted &amp;ldquo;hey, only 0.0027% of our visitors actually read up to Page 10, anyone who actually reads that far is three standard deviations away from normal, therefore they must be a web scraper!&amp;rdquo; and recommend punitive action accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noted earlier that it definitely was not a technical limitation that kept pages greater than 10 from being accessed. If you look at the URLs of the BuzzFeed screenshots above, you&amp;rsquo;ll notice a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;p=2&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; parameter for Page 2 or a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;p=10&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; parameter for Page 10. What happens if you just change the 10 to a 11?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You go to Page 11. And you can go all the way to page &lt;em&gt;200&lt;/em&gt; in some categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_200.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, this is easier and more reliable to implement programmatically than searching for the Older button and extracting the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the disabling of the button will only stop stupid web scrapers. Yes, that makes my BuzzFeed web scraper a stupid web scraper, &lt;em&gt;but that&amp;rsquo;s not the point!&lt;/em&gt; It just makes the BuzzFeed&amp;rsquo;s motive behind disabling the button at Page 10 even more baffling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did I do now that my quick-and-dirty BuzzFeed scraper couldn&amp;rsquo;t parse a statistically significant amount of BuzzFeed articles? I did the only logical thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a weekend learning how to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BeautifulSoup&lt;/a&gt; in Python and parsed BuzzFeed the hard way, while changing the page number in the URL to pagenate through the pages. And I even was able to add new features to the scraper, such as simultaneously scraping the number of Facebook Shares a given BuzzFeed article generates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_listicles.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a relationship between listicle size and social media engagement!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>