<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hacker News on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/tags/hacker-news/</link><description>Recent content in Hacker News on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://minimaxir.com/tags/hacker-news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Quality, Popularity, and Negativity of 5.6 Million Hacker News Comments</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/10/hn-comments-about-comments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/10/hn-comments-about-comments/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Last February, I &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published an article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, a tech-oriented link aggregator run by startup accelerator &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ycombinator.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;. In that post, I analyzed all submissions to date, and noted that the site has a strong and active userbase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent months, however, Hacker News has undergone criticism. A blog post by Danilo Campos titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://danilocampos.com/2014/09/y-combinator-and-the-negative-externalities-of-hacker-news/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Y Combinator and the negative externalities of Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, notes that although Hacker News is a critical resource for young male techies based in Silicon Valley (&lt;em&gt;Disclosure: I am a young male techie based in Silicon Valley&lt;/em&gt;), this has the consequence of excluding female hackers. Campos has even created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%23hnwatch&amp;amp;src=typd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;#HNwatch&lt;/a&gt; hashtag to catalog sexist and insensitive comments made by Hacker News users. As a long-time &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;user on Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, I unfortunately &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir/status/468080907925340160&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;agree with this assessment&lt;/a&gt; at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fairness, such comments are in the minority on Hacker News. Or are they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to better assess the quality, popularity, and negativity of Hacker News comments over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve downloaded 5,592,362 comments from Hacker News, the maximum number of comments possible, from its beginnings in 2006 to October 2014. Hopefully, these comments will answer whether Hacker News is experiencing a rise in quality, or if the complaints levied against HN are valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZwonVX_KlDYhuhPnAAnVpdVRgu4LxldP74-c_kvOd5k/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;glance at Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s best comments&lt;/a&gt;, determined by the number of upvotes it receives from the Hacker News community, for each month since 2006:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZwonVX_KlDYhuhPnAAnVpdVRgu4LxldP74-c_kvOd5k/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are interesting trends in this sample data set. The types of comments that became popular in 2006-2008 Hacker News were one-line quips, akin to those you would see in the comments on modern Reddit (which is a topic for another blog post). Highly-voted comments often come from the same people, especially those from Paul Graham (pg), Founder and then-President of Y Combinator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/early_reddit.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may indicate a bias or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halo_effect&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;halo effect&lt;/a&gt; where the commenter is more impactful than the comment itself. Additionally, some comments received many upvotes due to context: the top comment in December 2010 was simply &amp;ldquo;sad.&amp;rdquo; in a thread about &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2013248&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yahoo Shutting Down Delicious&lt;/a&gt;, but the comment was made by Joshua Schachter (joshu), the creator of Delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare those older comments to those made between 2012-2014. Those comments are very long, insightful, and made by many different people. (including a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4689643&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;comment by Danilo Campos himself&lt;/a&gt; in October 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these are the good comments. The bad comments are &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1IfbSDYVBXiHZCuMdHXgprhmeCVc4XDtOGizF9CSGyUo/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;set of Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s worst comments&lt;/a&gt; from each month where the comment has received a score of -3 or -4, the lowest score before the comment is automatically killed. (&lt;em&gt;Warning: comments may cause you to lose faith in humanity and/or be unintentionally hilarious&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1IfbSDYVBXiHZCuMdHXgprhmeCVc4XDtOGizF9CSGyUo/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The types of bad comments haven&amp;rsquo;t changed over the years. Hostile comments are immediately downvoted. It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that on Hacker News, you can be downvoted for being factually wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some users are more active commenters than others. Out of Hacker News&amp;rsquo;s 176,692 users who have made atleast 1 comment, only 48% of those commenters end up leaving two more comments, and only 6% of HN users end up leaving 100 or more comments total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/n-comments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as users comment more on Hacker News and learn the intricacies of HN&amp;rsquo;s culture, they become more skilled at creating quality comments which receive higher scores, which serve as an indicator of quality. As Hacker News users comment more and more, the average expected comment score for each successive post increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/n-comments-practice.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(The faded area for all charts in this article represents a 95% confidence interval for the average at a given point; all of the confidence intervals are very narrow due to the sheer quantity of data present. Whoo, big data!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the trends behind the Hacker News comments? First, we must see how Hacker News comments has changed over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hacking-through-the-years&#34;&gt;Hacking Through The Years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one would expect, the number of new comments posted on Hacker News each month has been gradually increasing proportional to its popularity, although the number of new comments per month has decreased starting in 2014, which indicates a slowing growth rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_total_comments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, has Hacker News retained quality with its increasing notoriety? One way to check is to analyze the average amount of points of the comments. Hacker News comments start out at 1 point, and other users can upvote and downvote comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_average_points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimum average points score of any given comment was about 2 points, meaning that all comments received atleast 1 upvote on average. This trend has been increasing until 2011 when it peaked at about 4.5 points. Since then, the average has trended downward, with a particularly large drop starting at 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, starting in 2014, both quantity &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; quality are on a downward trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to gauge quality is to look at the average comment length. Are comments trending toward short quips, or are longform comments more popular?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_average_words.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The length of the average comment has increased by about 10% over the years, which shows a slight increase in the overall thoughtfulness of HN comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has the average sentiment on Hacker News changed over the years? To gauge the relative sentiment of Hacker News comments, I compared each word of the comment against a lexicon of positive/negative words, and counted the number of review words in the lexicon. In this case, I used the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.uic.edu/~liub/FBS/sentiment-analysis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;lexicons compiled by UIC professor Bing Liu&lt;/a&gt;. This is the same method used in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/one-star-five-stars/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous analysis of Yelp reviews&lt;/a&gt;, where the technique was very effective. However, unlike Yelp, comments on Hacker News tend to make use of sarcasm, so this method may be less effective. (there isn&amp;rsquo;t any easy method for detecting sarcasm, because who in the entire world would want an easy method for detecting sarcasm?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that, we can calculate average positivity and average negativity for a given comment by dividing the number of positive/negative words respectively by the approximate number of words in the comment. Both metrics have converged slightly over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/monthly_average_positive_negative.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, the average positivity of a comment is &lt;em&gt;3.2%&lt;/em&gt;, while the average negativity of a comment is &lt;em&gt;2.3%&lt;/em&gt; (leading to a 0.9% net positive sentiment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of the comments Hacker News has definitely changed since the site&amp;rsquo;s humble beginnings in 2006, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to determine if it&amp;rsquo;s for the &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look more into the nature of the upvote system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-points&#34;&gt;Free Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, the number of points on a new Hacker News comment starts at 1 point. Anyone can give an upvote, which increases the points value by one. However, long-time HN users can downvote posts, decreasing the score by 1. Downvoting has another effect; comments with 0 or fewer points turn an aesthetically-displeasing gray, in an effort to both hide them from the public eye and encourage corrective upvotes if necessary from users with OCD. In all other cases, the points score of a comment is hidden from other users in order to help prevent bandwagoning and the upvoting of comments just because they have lots of upvotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/distribution_comment_points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over 50% of all comments simply have 1 or 2 points, with the proportion decreasing by a third for each successive point value. What&amp;rsquo;s surprising is how few comments have 0 or fewer points: this shows that HN users do not like downvoting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that comment length could be used a proxy for comment quality. Is there a relationship between the number of points a comment receives and the length of a comment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/distribution_comment_points_words.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, yes! The effect of comment length on the number of points a comment received is likely not solely causal, but the correlation between the two values is helpful. (it is statistically unlikely to receive a lot of upvotes if your comment is short. The inverse is also true; a short comment is much more likely get downvoted.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a similar correlation between sentiment and the number of points a comment receives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/distribution_comment_points_sentiment.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope. Both positivity and negativity are relatively static regardless of point values, although it&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that comments with 0 or fewer points (downvoted comments) have a disproportionately high negativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tone-and-tolerance-on-hacker-news&#34;&gt;Tone and Tolerance on Hacker News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a big difference between the language used in a Hacker News comment on a typical submission, and the language used in Hacker News submissions about women and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/hn_2_gram_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This word cloud consists of bigrams made from 109k comments from HN submissions in September 2014, and from 21k comments in threads whose submission title contains &amp;ldquo;women&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;female,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;diversity.&amp;rdquo; The language in the former is more neutral and about the content of the article (apparently Hacker News users &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like to talk about Open Source software), while the submissions about gender and diversity trend to talk about tangent topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does the tone differ between the two groups of articles? Here&amp;rsquo;s the distribution of the average number of positive words in comments per submission in September 2014:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/density_september_2014_hn.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average amount of positive words in a comment made in September 2014 is 2.16 words, and the average amount of negative words is 1.46, with both of those values being close to the respective statistical modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s compare that to the distribution of comments made on all submissions about women and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-comments/density_women.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average amount of positive words in a comment made in thread about gender and diversity is 2.48 words, a little higher than the average, and is also the most frequently occuring value. However, The average amount of positive words in a comment made in thread about gender and diversity is 2.10 words, a much higher increase. The average is to the right of the mode, indicating that the average is skewed-right by submissions with overly-negative comments. This may be why there is a greater perception of negativity for readers of comment threads about women and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/hackernews.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;stated goals of Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; is to avoid an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eternal_September&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eternal September&lt;/a&gt;, where the quality of discourse drops and everyone leaves. It&amp;rsquo;s clear that the quality of discourse has changed over the years: comments are longer, but not necessarily better. Positivity has decreased and negativity has increased. The difference between 2006 HN and 2014 HN is stark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News isn&amp;rsquo;t the perfect tech news aggregator. The issue of inclusion is real, and despite the fact that sexist comments are in the minority, they need to stop. In 2014, both quantity &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; quality are decreasing. But since that Y Combinator has &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ycombinator.com/diversity-and-startups&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;committed to ending sexism in tech&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ycombinator.com/meet-the-people-taking-over-hacker-news&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;appointed new moderators&lt;/a&gt; to control content quality, I&amp;rsquo;m confident that things will improve in the future for Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data was retrieved from Hacker News using &lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/api&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the official API&lt;/a&gt;. The data was then stored in a PostgreSQL database, mostly so I could take advantage of that database&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.1/static/tutorial-window.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;window functions&lt;/a&gt; capability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charts, word clouds, and other miscellaneous data processing was done using R and ggplot2. Gathering the data from the API and extracting the bigrams for the word clouds was done using Python.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can access the code used to process the data, chart the data, and extract bigrams from the comments in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/hacker-news-comment-analysis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. This does not include the code for retrieving the comments from the Hacker News API and storing it in PostgreSQL: that code will be in a separate repository if released.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Impact of the New Show HN Section on Show HN Submissions</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 08:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News, a tech-oriented link aggregator managed by Y Combinator, is a platform where software projects have launched to literally become multibillion-dollar companies. Submissions which contain the phrase &amp;ldquo;Show HN&amp;rdquo; usually designate a clever hack or weekend project. On &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ycombinator.com/make-things-and-show-them&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;July 3rd 2014&lt;/a&gt;, Hacker News &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/show&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;created a section of Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; just for these Show HN projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did this feature help or harm Show HN submissions as a whole?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, the average number of Show HN submissions per day has steadily risen. (this is strongly correlated with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;growth of Hacker News as a whole&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-submissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on that spike at the end later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Hacker News, users can upvote link submissions, which increases the point score of the submission; this point score is used as a rough proxy of link quality. The average amount of points per submission peaked in 2012, and has trended downward since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a chart of the points of Show HN submissions averaged by date of submission, then averaged across the previous 30-days to further smooth the variation and make the trend more apparent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can also comment on these Show HN posts. The average amount of comments has trended downward over time, albeit only slightly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-comments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of increased Show HN submissions and a decrease in point quality over time may imply that Show HN submissions have a low signal-to-noise ratio, i.e. a low amount of good submissions relative high amount of bad submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitting the front page of Hacker News is the first step to virality. When users upvote submissions on Hacker News, those submissions can hit the front page after achieving enough points (combined with other factors, such as submission age and quantity of other submissions). At the least, if a submission has 10 points, it has most likely hit the front page sometime in its lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What proportion of the Show HN submissions hit the front page?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-perc-front.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, the amount of good Show HNs relative to the amount of bad Show HNs has been steadily decreasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has the new Show HN feature helped improve the signal-to-noise ratio?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;show-and-tell-hn&#34;&gt;Show and Tell HN&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can look at the immediate impact of the new Show HN section by comparing the behavior of submissions before and after the announcement. The red area in the following charts represents the daily behavior in the couple months before the release (with the red horizontal dotted line representing the statistical average for the corresponding measurement), and the blue area/blue line represents the behavior after the release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Show HN feature was first announced, everyone rushed to make a submission to test it out, and it showed. In fact, the number of submissions for every day after the feature was added was greater than the average number of submissions from before the addition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-submissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average number of daily submissions before Show HN section is &lt;strong&gt;19.13&lt;/strong&gt; submissions/day, average after is &lt;strong&gt;53.44&lt;/strong&gt; submissions/day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average submission points and average submission comments (both aggregated by date of submission for smoothing) received a slight boost too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-comments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average number of daily points before Show HN section is &lt;strong&gt;11.40&lt;/strong&gt; points/submission/day, average after is &lt;strong&gt;12.12&lt;/strong&gt; points/submission/day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average number of daily comments before Show HN section is &lt;strong&gt;6.57&lt;/strong&gt; comments/submission/day, average after is &lt;strong&gt;7.16&lt;/strong&gt; comments/submission/day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The percentage of Show HN submissions that hit the front page, however, moves in a different direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-perc-front.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average daily % of Show HN submissions which hit the front page before Show HN section is &lt;strong&gt;19.33%&lt;/strong&gt;, average after is &lt;strong&gt;16.37%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Show HN section gives more focus to Show HN submissions, the increased motivation for making Show HN submissions does not necessarily imply that the submissions will be better. It will take more time to see of the downward trend of Show HN quality continues over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data was processed using R and all charts were made using ggplot2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view the data of all the Show HN submissions and the derived moving averages &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1JHIlzYdsavWnw8Y5efHrOHCo3-WFGtIosJ2WqIV_Bn4/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in this Google Sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view code necessary to reproduce these results and reproduce all the charts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/show-hn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. This repository also includes a .csv of all ~20,000 Show HNs obtained.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Statistical Analysis of All Hacker News Submissions</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/news&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; is a very popular link aggregator for the technology and startup community. Officially titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://ycombinator.com/hackernews.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;by Paul Graham in 2007&lt;/a&gt;, Hacker News began mostly as a place where the very computational-savvy could submit stories around the internet and discuss the latest computing trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-wordcloud-2007i.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, people were talking about networking, software users, and a little up-and-coming startup known as &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six years later, during the new renaissance of computing accessibility and startup entrepreneurship, not much has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-wordcloud-2013i.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News, from 2007 to 2014, always illustrates what&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; in technology. After downloading all 1,265,114 Hacker News submissions from the official &lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/api&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hacker News API&lt;/a&gt;, I gathered a few interesting statistics which show the true impact of Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-many-stories-are-submitted-to-hacker-news&#34;&gt;How many stories are submitted to Hacker News?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, Hacker News has had an interesting growth pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-monthly-submissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of 2010 with 12k monthly submissions to to the end of 2011 with 31k monthly submissions, the amount of monthly submissions to Hacker News nearly tripled. It&amp;rsquo;s a similar growth rate to that of the startups that Y Combinator typically funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; interesting is that the end of 2011 is the peak: since then, the amount of submissions has been trending downward. Is Hacker News dying?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think so. Hacker News implements a proprietary anti-spam algorithm which &amp;ldquo;kills&amp;rdquo; submissions, and moderators can kill submissions manually if necessary. Killed articles do not appear in the submission count, so a change in policy would cause the discrepancy. At the least, it helps improve the quality of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE (2/28): Paul Graham, in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7291531&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;corresponding HN thread&lt;/a&gt;, made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7292094&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; that the anti-spam algorithm did indeed increase spam detection and number of article killed at the end of 2011.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-many-submissions-receive-large-amounts-of-points&#34;&gt;How many submissions receive large amounts of points?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Hacker News, users are able to upvote submissions. The more upvotes a submission has, the higher the position that it appears on the front page of the main site. A simple heuristic for calculating exposure from a Hacker News front page submission is 100 page views per point minimum, which means a submission that earns hundreds of points can go viral very quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hntop.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how many submissions actually make it to the front page, and how many actually make it to the top?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-points-hist.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a logarithmic scale, it&amp;rsquo;s evident that the vast majority of Hacker News submissions don&amp;rsquo;t even hit 10 points. (the average amount of points for a submission is 9.51). Usually, hitting 10 points is the sign that you&amp;rsquo;ve appeared on the front page atleast briefly; there, the submission either receives voting momentum or dies quickly due to other rising stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how many submissions &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; receive hundreds of points? Here&amp;rsquo;s a chart of submissions by month which have received more than 100 points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-monthly-submissions-front.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of top-scoring submissions is correlated with the growth rate of Hacker News submissions themselves, which is not surprising. The number of points a post receives is also dependent on the number of users; as Hacker News grows, the number of users grows as well. Even though the front page cycles frequently, there is still room for great content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-is-the-best-time-to-submit-to-hacker-news&#34;&gt;When is the best time to submit to Hacker News?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The age old question. What is the best time to post such that your post makes it to the front page?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;rsquo;s see when Hacker News has the most activity by observing the average number of submissions for each combination of submission hour and weekday:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-submissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News activity is most active at around 12 PM EST / 9 AM PST at about 40 submissions per hour, when hackers on the East Coast submit just before eating lunch, and hackers on the West Coast submit just after getting to work. Weekends, unsurprisingly, are completely dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you submitted your link at 12 PM, you&amp;rsquo;d have a lot competition, but it would be easier to get upvotes since there would be more people visiting the site. If you submitted your post on the weekend, there would be no competition, but would be harder to make the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the best weekday + hour to submit such that your submission goes viral? An easy way to estimate the best time is to analyze the times of submission of previous posts with large amounts of points; with enough data (we have enough), it&amp;rsquo;ll provide a strong guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-front-page.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the submission times of posts are &lt;em&gt;uncorrelated&lt;/em&gt; with the number of viral posts. There are &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; more when submitting at peak activity (weekdays at 12 PM EST / 9 AM PST), but it won&amp;rsquo;t make-or-break an article&amp;rsquo;s success on HN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having good content is more important to having a post get to the top of Hacker News. Although you probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t submit an article when there&amp;rsquo;s a major tech event. (e.g. Facebook&amp;rsquo;s WhatsApp Purchase)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE (2/28): It&amp;rsquo;s been pointed out that measuring the proportion of viral posts (number of viral submissions / number of total submissions) would be a better indicator of odds of article success. Since the number of viral submissions is similar across all time zones, the proportion of viral posts would be greatest on the weekends, since there are dramatically fewer total submissions. However, this logic isn&amp;rsquo;t perfectly correct due to how the article discovery and upvoting system works. I may cover this in a future post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-y-combinator-startup-announcements-score-better-on-hn&#34;&gt;Do Y Combinator startup announcements score better on HN?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main benefits of Hacker News is to showcase the startups which Y Combinator has funded. Links about YC Startups contain the YC class name of that startup in their title, such as &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6103506&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Watsi (YC W13) raises $1.2M first-of-its-kind philanthropic seed round&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Do these links perform better than the typical links submitted to Hacker News?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-points-class-hist.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, yes. For normal posts, the average number of points is 9.5 points, but for YC class announcements, the average is 41.7 points (from 1,745 submissions analyzed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For fun, which YC classes perform the best on Hacker News?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-top-class.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W06 placed first because of &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2481576&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2481610&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announcements&lt;/a&gt; about Wufoo, and S11 placed second because of &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6585071&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CryptoSeal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2846725&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Parse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-are-the-best-submitters-on-hacker-news&#34;&gt;Who are the best submitters on Hacker News?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all popular link aggregators, Hacker News has many spammers who submit large amounts of low quality content. Who are the users who submit quality content?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculating the average points of a user&amp;rsquo;s submitted content isn&amp;rsquo;t an accurate measurement, since that can be heavily skewed by one viral post. Therefore, I created a Hacker News &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batting_average&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;batting average&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; statistic: which posters have the highest proportion of posts that make it to the front page vs. the total number submitted? (for posts since 2010 and number of submitted posts &amp;gt;= 10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-top-submitters.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be no surprise that most of the people on the list are startup founders. It&amp;rsquo;s also not surprising that most of those founders, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=mwseibel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mwseibel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=rahulvohra&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rahulvohra&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=tikhon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tikhon&lt;/a&gt; also founded a Y Combinator startup. (although Paul Graham &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=pg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;himself&lt;/a&gt; only has a 0.856 average).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-hacker-news-favorite-programming-languages&#34;&gt;What are Hacker News&amp;rsquo; favorite programming languages?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the infamous memes about Hacker News is programming language elitism, with favoritism for languages such as Lisp and Erlang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what programming languages are indeed the most popular on Hacker News?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-lang-num-submissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Javascript is very popular, especially with the rising popularity of node.js. Go is unexpectedly frequently submitted for being such a new language. (although it&amp;rsquo;s possible for &amp;ldquo;go&amp;rdquo; to be used in a context outside of a programing language.) Lisp and Erlang are indeed obscure, which might discredit the meme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which programming languages are most well-liked on HN?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-lang-avg-submissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;so Lisp and Erlang &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; well-liked on HN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the least, in both cases, no one on Hacker News likes PHP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;snowden-and-bitcoin&#34;&gt;Snowden and Bitcoin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s leaks in June 2013 about the NSA and PRISM affected the entire tech industry, including Hacker News. How did Hacker News react to the leaks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-snowden.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strongly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the June spike, discussion about the NSA decreased significantly, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a popular topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is more interesting since it has had three distinct surges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/hn-bitcoin.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The June 2011 spike was due to the theft of &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?topic=16457.0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;25,000 Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt;, the April 2013 spike happened during the first rise-and-fall from $200/BTC, and the November 2013 spike happened during the second rise-and-fall from $1,000/BTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News is a great model for a link aggregator. It emphasizes more on quality content than the quantity of content, and it has paid off over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Code for getting all the HN submissions is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/hacker-news-download-all-stories&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, the Hacker News data is too large to distribute freely. &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/contact/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Contact me&lt;/a&gt; if you want the raw data or any data to reproduce the charts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: there appear to be &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Zdex42KE-8DFIHujhVWjJ3yqilJSws2EbT8VAARPYgE/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;some gaps in the data&lt;/a&gt; for dates before 2010. This appears to be caused by the API server: for example, compare the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=liebke&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;number of submissions as reported by HN for top user liebke&lt;/a&gt; (21) and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=story,author_liebke&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;number of submissions as reported by the API&lt;/a&gt; for liebke (14, with the last 7 submitted stories missing relative to the HN output). Also, number of stories (1,265,114) in the output data and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hn.algolia.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;server data&lt;/a&gt; (~1,267,000 as of publishing) are very close, making the discrepancy unlikely caused by client error. As a result, any chart that is based on a time series does not start earlier than 2010.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>