<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Gaming on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>/categories/gaming/</link><description>Recent content in Gaming on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/gaming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>When Uninstalling A PC Game Erases the Entire Hard Drive</title><link>/2013/06/working-as-intended/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/06/working-as-intended/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;There are many legitimate reasons for users to uninstall programs on their computer, such as freeing hard-disk space and lowering CPU overhead. A decade ago, when excessive hard-drive space was a luxury, avid PC gamers would frequently uninstall large, multi-gigabyte games that they were no longer playing in order to make space for new games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, developers would prefer that their users not uninstall the software that they spent years creating. Regardless, developers should ensure that the uninstall process works properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, a poorly coded PC game uninstaller could delete not just the game, but the &lt;em&gt;entire hard drive&lt;/em&gt;. That would be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ragnarok&#34;&gt;Ragnarok&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/1999/01/06&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/pennyarcademyth2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 1998, Bungie (which would later create the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halowaypoint.com/en-us/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Halo&lt;/a&gt; series) released &lt;a href=&#34;http://mythipedia.wikia.com/wiki/Myth_II:_Soulblighter&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Myth II: Soulblighter&lt;/a&gt; for Windows. Myth II, a real-time tactics game, was received with great reception and highly-positive reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before the worldwide release, a Bungie employee &lt;a href=&#34;http://halo.bungie.net/inside/history.aspx?link=juggernougat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;uninstalled version 1.0&lt;/a&gt; of Myth II, and afterwards, her PC refused to reboot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was discovered by a very nice young lady in a Japanese office as she worked on the Asian versions of Myth – just as she was trying out the final build. She attempted to uninstall it from the main root folder of her hard drive – not brilliant, but pretty common practice – and perfectly fine for most games. The game proceeded to eat her hard drive like a fresh Bento Box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Myth II Uninstaller worked by deleting the folder which contained the game files. However, this implementation assumed that the user installed Myth II in the default directory. (i.e. C:\Program Files\Myth II). If the user installed Myth II in a &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; directory, such as the *system root C:\*, then when the user uninstalled the game, &lt;strong&gt;all the files in the C drive were deleted.&lt;/strong&gt; Boom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Bungie later explained &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.macobserver.com/news/98/december/981229/bungierecall.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;in a press release&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In certain unusual cases, using the Uninstaller can cause problems. If a user chooses an installation directory other than the default directory, they should NOT use the Uninstaller but should manually drag the Myth II folder into the Recycle bin and delete it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has the game but has not yet installed it is asked to wait for a new version of the Installer which we will release shortly. If you have already installed the game, there is no harm in playing it, but players should be careful not to use the Uninstall executable. If you have already Uninstalled and not experienced obvious problems, there is nothing to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calling the potential obliteration of an operating system a &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; is an understatement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the issue was not widespread, Bungie decided to do a recall of all Myth II CDs and redistribute a version 1.1, eliminating most of the game&amp;rsquo;s profits in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could say that the Myth II version 1.0 uninstaller worked exactly as intended: it did indeed uninstall the game. It just worked &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE October 2014&lt;/strong&gt;: A year after this article was posted, someone submitted this article to the Reddit subreddit &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;todayilearned&lt;/a&gt;, where it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned/comments/2ka43x/til_that_in_the_game_myth_ii_soulblighter_due_to/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;subsequently went viral&lt;/a&gt;. In the comments, Reddit user rdmartell, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freelancer.com/u/rdmartell.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;former developer at Bungie&lt;/a&gt;, posted more insight into the glitch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I wrote the Myth TFL installer (not this one). The reason this happened is because you could install other maps and whatnot, and to make the uninstall clean, we had to recursively delete your data folder.
In the sequel, somehow that code (which did sanity checks) was used to delete the applications directory, instead of just the data directory in the applications directory.
So if you installed it on C:/, it would delete everything recursively from there.
Nowadays, uninstall usually leaves any user installed files (like saves or downloaded content) but at the time, as the article suggests, hard drive space was more precious. Also, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t there for this issue, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know the above for sure, but having written the previous installer, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty confident that&amp;rsquo;s what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the thread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually think the bug was only there if you installed directly to root; not even in a folder. As I recall, that was the only way it deleted your entire HDD.
Unless it was discovered later by going into the uninstalled code that it could happen in other cases (which I never heard about), I think the issue was a bit overblown by the media. Still, the last thing you want to be responsible for is nuking a customer&amp;rsquo;s hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small world.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Role-Playing Game With an Easily Exploitable Random Number Generator</title><link>/2013/05/guaranteed-to-be-random/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 20:26:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/guaranteed-to-be-random/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/GoldenSun.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Game Boy Advance was released in June 2001, Nintendo promised that the handheld device would be capable of delivering a home gaming console experience on-the-go. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Golden Sun&lt;/a&gt;, developed by Camelot and published by Nintendo a few months after the console&amp;rsquo;s release, exemplified the GBA&amp;rsquo;s full capabilities with its hand-drawn environments, flashy battle effects, and &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; difficult dungeon puzzles which undoubtedly resulted in the sale of many strategy guides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Golden Sun, you play as a group of teenage mages called Adepts, who wield the power of the four elements (Earth, Fire, Wind, and Water) by casting spells with Psynergy. The antagonists of the game are a pair of jerks who are attempting to reawaken a dangerous and sealed power, and only four kids can stop them from destroying the world. Released two years later, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun:_The_Lost_Age&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Golden Sun: The Lost Age&lt;/a&gt; takes place immediately after the conclusion of the first game with a different quartet of Adepts and a new pair of jerks. In this sequel, it is revealed that the jerks who keep trying to kill you are not the bad guys and the whole conflict is just one big misunderstanding! Yes, the plot is very reminiscent of other Japanese-developed RPGs such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_(video_game)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Final Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrono_Trigger&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chrono Trigger&lt;/a&gt;, but it&amp;rsquo;s still impressive for a game I typically played in the backseat of a car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Final Fantasy and Chrono Trigger, Golden Sun has an inventory system where players earn new weapons and items by purchasing them at a store or by finding them as loot from defeating enemies in the world. The most powerful weapons, naturally, only drop from enemies at the end of the game with odds of less than 0.01% per kill. If you killed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=binomial+distribution%28100%2C1%2F256%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;such enemies 100 times&lt;/a&gt;, for example, you would only have a 32% expected chance of seeing a rare drop among all the kills. And killing that many enemies could take hours. It depends on the almighty will of Golden Sun&amp;rsquo;s Random Number Generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Random_Number_Generator&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Golden Sun RNG&lt;/a&gt; is so poorly implemented that players have found out how to make events with &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;256&lt;/sub&gt; probability occur &lt;em&gt;one hundred percent&lt;/em&gt; of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-make-your-own-luck&#34;&gt;You Make Your Own Luck&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/221/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/random_number.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after the first Golden Sun was released, players discovered that the first random enemy encounter the player enters after turning the GBA on was always a First Strike, where the player&amp;rsquo;s party gets a free turn. Was this a cute gameplay mechanic intended to give the player a quick advantage, or was it indicative of a flaw in the game&amp;rsquo;s RNG?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most modern RNGs are partially seeded and randomized using a timer, i.e. the current time of the computer in microseconds. This makes it infeasable to reproduce the output of the RNG reliably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the GBA does not have an internal clock, so time-based methods of seeding aren&amp;rsquo;t possible. By the time the sequel was released in 2003, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goldensunrealm.com/gs/nickpresta_rng-guide.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;entire Golden Sun RNG&lt;/a&gt; was reverse-engineered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Golden Sun uses the ANSI-C standard rand function as its Pseudo-Random Number
Generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one difference: Golden Sun&amp;rsquo;s RNG uses an unsigned 4-byte number and
returns it with no shifting, so you&amp;rsquo;d replace &amp;ldquo;return ((next &amp;gt;&amp;gt;16) &amp;amp; 32757);&amp;rdquo;
with &amp;ldquo;return (next &amp;amp; 4294967295);&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, ordinarily, is a perfectly capable RNG, but there is one flaw with what
Golden Sun does with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It only makes a new random number when something random happens. What&amp;rsquo;s more,
it uses &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; copies of the RNG to create two random numbers, and the
first RNG only handles battle situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, it is easy to control when a new random number is generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of this, the RNGs are seeded with 0 when the GBA is reset, and because
of the way the game has been programmed, the RNG controlling battle events will
&lt;em&gt;continue&lt;/em&gt; to be 0 even when you load the game&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Golden Sun&amp;rsquo;s Random Number Generator isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;random&amp;rdquo; at all. It&amp;rsquo;s manipulated &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; from player-controlled actions, from the moment the Game Boy Advance is turned on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-lucky&#34;&gt;Get Lucky&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/kiku.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Golden Sun&amp;rsquo;s contributions to the typical RPG character class customization is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Djinn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Djinn system&lt;/a&gt;. In the game lore, Djinn are impish creatures that grant enhanced powers to Adepts. There are four types of Djinn, one for each element, that can be found in the overworld, and each Djinni can be used to either increase a character&amp;rsquo;s statistics, or Unleashed to provide a powerful spell effect. Also, as with many other RPGs, Golden Sun implements an elemental rock-paper-scissors combat system: enemies are weak to an element and resistant to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gamefaqs.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GameFAQs&lt;/a&gt; forum user by the name of &amp;ldquo;darkpanther&amp;rdquo; discovered that using a Djinn Unleash with an element that is the enemy&amp;rsquo;s weakness will not only increase the amount of Experience and Coins earned, but also &lt;em&gt;quadruple&lt;/em&gt; the chance of the enemy dropping a rare item. (this fact is neither hinted anywhere in the game nor stated in any strategy guides)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is essential toward manipulating the RNG. Normally, the rarest items such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Tisiphone_Edge&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tisiphone Edge&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Lachesis%27_Rule&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Lachesis&amp;rsquo; Rule&lt;/a&gt; have an &amp;ldquo;Item-Class Chance&amp;rdquo; of 9, meaning the item has a 1/(2&lt;sup&gt;9-1&lt;/sup&gt;) = &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;256&lt;/sub&gt; chance of dropping per enemy kill. The &amp;ldquo;DP Method&amp;rdquo; decreases the ICC by 2, meaning the new drop rate becomes 1/(2&lt;sup&gt;7-1&lt;/sup&gt;) = &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;64&lt;/sub&gt;. But:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &amp;lsquo;unpredictable&amp;rsquo; as RNGs seem to be, if they are always seeded to the same
value and do not use a timer-based response, they will become predictable by
anyone who is good at noticing patterns. One pattern being, for example, that
the 31st random number that is calculated - 33727075 - will drop &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; item if
the enemy dying when this random number was called was just killed by an
elemental Djinn attack that it is weak to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculating the 31st random number would fail against an ICC9 item, but now works against an ICC7 item. (and all items of lower ICC too)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, &lt;strong&gt;in order to guarantee that an item drops, kill the appropriate enemy with an element-advantage Djinni such that the 30th random number is generated&lt;/strong&gt;. (the 31st random number is generated on the enemy&amp;rsquo;s death)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you ensure that you only create 31 random numbers? From the Golden Sun Wikia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save the game and do a hard reset in the area where the monster that drops the item you need appears. Run around to get in a battle. If the encounter consists of a formation of 2 monsters, with at least one of them being the monster you want, proceed. If not, do another hard reset and try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During battle, have the entire party use multi-targetting Psynergy on the targets in the first turn, and since a battle right after a hard reset always involve your party attacking first where possible, the monsters will not be able to act. During the second turn, use two multi-targetting Psynergy on the enemies, and have the third party member (or fourth, if one of the three party members that act before uses Defend) unleash an attack Djinni of the element the monster is weak to on the monster. If by this point, the monster flashes in colour and dies, you will obtain the drop of that monster at the end of the battle, however rare it is. If the monster does not die then (either dies too soon or doesn&amp;rsquo;t die by this step), adjust the power of your attacks until you get it just right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/UCJzuSBQ1hU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral of story: if you&amp;rsquo;re making a video game, seed your RNGs with an algorithm that players can&amp;rsquo;t manipulate 100%. Otherwise, hilarity will inevitably ensue. I forgive Camelot for implementing a simplistic RNG though; the two games&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DaxYYwMqiso&amp;amp;list=PL8C84ECF55B28DC74&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M31afGXIGpQ&amp;amp;list=PL586792F46D5A35D4&amp;amp;index=13&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;soundtrack &lt;/a&gt; more than makes up for it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Profanity-Laced Video Game Password That Breaks Everything</title><link>/2013/05/its-a-livin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 20:50:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/its-a-livin/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/metroidboxart.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of video games, you&amp;rsquo;ve likely heard of the Metroid franchise. Released for the NES in 1986 by Nintendo, Metroid set a new standard for 2-D exploration in video games with its expansive power-up system, well-hidden secrets, and polished platforming controls. Due to its popularity, Metroid has been rereleased multiple times: as an unlockable in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Prime&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metroid Prime&lt;/a&gt;, an unlockable in the remake &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Zero_Mission&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metroid: Zero Mission&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classic_NES_Series&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;standalone game&lt;/a&gt; on the Game Boy Advance, the Wii Virtual Console, and the 3DS Virtual Console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You play as Samus Aran, an armored bounty hunter who has infiltrated the base of the dreaded Space Pirates on Planet Zebes. Samus must defeat the leaders of the Space Pirates: the dinosaur Kraid, the dragon and memetic badass of the series &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridley_(Metroid)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ridley&lt;/a&gt;, and the AI construct &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_Brain_(Metroid)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mother Brain&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, Samus must find a way to defeat the Metroids, which are nearly-indestructible parasites that threaten all life. Yes, this was a plot written in the 80&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the NES Metroid cartridge did not have the ability to save games, and the game itself took awhile to complete, Nintendo developed a password system to allow players to continue at a later time. Upon death, the player received a 24-character alphanumeric password that could be entered to restore all items the player has unlocked and remember which bosses the player has defeated. Most of these passwords were gibberish that required a pen-and-paper to write down and remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One password, however, is more memorable, and much more sinister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-password-is-always-swordfish&#34;&gt;The Password is Always Swordfish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the days of the internet and personal computing, players &lt;a href=&#34;http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/List_of_Metroid_passwords&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;found passwords&lt;/a&gt; with unique properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Narpas_Sword&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Narpas Sword password&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/narpassword.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is essentially the debug mode for the game, with all items unlocked, infinite health, and infinite health for Samus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, more revealing password is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Justin_Bailey&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Justin Bailey password&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justinbailey.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This password starts the game with most unlockables obtained, but more notably, it changes Samus&amp;rsquo;s sprite from an armored powersuit to a bikini swimsuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One password, discovered over 20 years later, long after the Metroid password system had been completely reverse-engineered, does not grant you all items. &lt;em&gt;This&lt;/em&gt; password just crashes and resets the game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/engageridley.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wtf&#34;&gt;WTF?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a NES and various other rereleases, inputting that code will cause the game to either simply reset or transform the game into a glitched wonderland:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x3UyVylP7AI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what happens when you enter the password on an emulated Virtual Console, where the game environment is sandboxed? In the case of the 3DS Virtual Console, the &lt;em&gt;3DS completely crashes&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/pjQ7SjB_6a8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rated-e-for-everyone&#34;&gt;Rated E for Everyone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be asking &amp;ldquo;did someone at Nintendo actually program a consequence for profanity in the game? Is the glitching and crashing a punishment for the perverse player?&amp;rdquo; In truth, the password is merely a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, the password algorithm for Metroid has been reverse-engineered, and you can actually download a program to both generate and interpret such passwords &lt;a href=&#34;http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/metroidpassgen.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The profane password is indeed a legitimate password (in which Ridley is already defeated, ironically enough). But why does it crash the game? The &lt;a href=&#34;http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/password.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metroid Password Format Guide&lt;/a&gt; explains the secret:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are five valid start locations. They are specified using bits 64-66.
To start in Brinstar, all the bits should be off. Norfair, Kraid&amp;rsquo;s Lair, and
Ridley&amp;rsquo;s Lair can be specified by turning their bit on and leaving the others
off. Tourian is specified by turning on Norfair and Kraid&amp;rsquo;s Lair
simultaneously. Any other combination of these three bits is invalid and will
cause Metroid to reset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reset bit is part of the start location. There are 16 possible values,
but only 5 valid ones. Turning on the reset bit will produce and invalid
start location and cause Metroid to reset. This is why it is called it is
called the reset bit, because it guarantees an invalid password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the profane password, the reset bit is turned on, so it will always cause a reset. And that&amp;rsquo;s why the weird behavior happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you manually disable the reset bit using this tool in order to make the password valid, the new password becomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/metroidpassgen2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not as catchy, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the Justin Bailey password is also a completely coincidental password. Sometimes, passwords can just do very unexpected things.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Diablo III Economy Broken by an Integer Overflow Bug</title><link>/2013/05/stones-of-jordan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 21:53:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/stones-of-jordan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://us.battle.net/d3/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Diablo III&lt;/a&gt;, Blizzard&amp;rsquo;s highly-awaited online-only Action RPG released almost a year ago to the day, has had its share of technical difficulties. From &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/error-37&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Error 37&lt;/a&gt; to lag spikes that can cause hundreds of hours to go to waste, Blizzard has spent the past year improving the game backend to better accommidate the millions of active players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diablo III is also noted for its economy, with an emphasis on a region-wide auction house where players can trade one-in-a-million items for millions and billions of gold. (inflation is crazy). Additionally, Diablo III emphasized the use of a Real World Auction House, where players can sell gold or items for real world cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was the launch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.battle.net/d3/en/blog/9647272/patch-108-now-live-5-7-2013&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Patch 1.0.8&lt;/a&gt;, a patch which promised improvements to character progression. After spending a few weeks on a Public Test Realm, where players volunteered to tested the patch to ensure that there were game-breaking exploits, the patch released successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except for one patch note that was added last minute and not tested in the PTR. And it&amp;rsquo;s a patch note that broke the economy to tiny pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patch notes from the final build contained this change:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stack size for gold sales on the auction house has been increased from 1 million to 10 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, on the Real Money Auction House, the player can only sell money in 1 million gold increments. In 1.0.8, the player can sell it in 10 million increments. So, what happens when the player tries putting an absurd amount of money on the Auction House?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reddit user tyropro &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dx3wv/some_speculation_on_how_the_gold_bug_made_it_to/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;has a nice explanation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gold &amp;ldquo;dupe&amp;rdquo; involved creating a RMAH auction for billions of gold while staying under the $250 limit. The example I saw in a video was 6 billion gold (600 x 10,000,000 at $0.39 per stack, for $234). When they posted this auction only ~1.7 billion appeared to be for sale, with the rest &amp;ldquo;missing&amp;rdquo; until they sent it to their stash and ended up with more than they started with. The exact numbers from a duping video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Create RMAH auction for: 6,000,000,000 gold
Auction shows up as: 1,705,032,704 gold
This much is missing! 4,294,967,296 gold
The missing amount, divided by 2: 2,147,483,648 gold
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2,147,483,648 (or 231) is the maximum value you can store in an int32 in programming. I&amp;rsquo;m no programmer, but I took one class in high school and was taught about the limits of different variable types. See:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, their RMAH gold selling code wasn&amp;rsquo;t written to handle numbers over 2,147,483,648 properly, and the result was duplicate gold being added to people&amp;rsquo;s stashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4,294,967,296 is also 232, or the bound on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integer_(computer_science)#Common_long_integer_sizes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unsigned integer&lt;/a&gt;, which would be an interesting implementation choice on Blizzard&amp;rsquo;s part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, the dupers created these 6-billion-gold auctions which only appears to sell as 1.7 billion (and therefore only had 1.7 billion deducted from the current balance), canceled them, and were fully refunded the 6 billion for a net profit of the difference (4.2 billion). Repeat &lt;em&gt;ad nauseum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popular game streamer showed off the exploit. Other streamers followed. It was easily reproducible and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dw9kr/there_is_a_gold_dupe_on_na_currently_this_is_the/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;everyone knew how to reproduce it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hilarity ensued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/diablo31.png&#34; alt=&#34;diablo31&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s 420 &lt;em&gt;billion&lt;/em&gt; gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After buying up all the duped items in the Auction House, the items were then sold on the Real Money Auction House. For real money. And people bought them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the definition of a worst-case scenario for Diablo III. All because of an untested patch note. What could Blizzard do? Performing a roll-back would wipe all progress obtained by players for the patch day, which would result in a lot of bad PR. But leaving the economy as-is will devalue all items in the game (and Diablo III is all about getting items).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, Blizzard &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dx4a7/there_will_officially_be_no_rollback_after_the/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;has not done a roll-back&lt;/a&gt;, but instead &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dwk6x/d3_inigomontoya_just_got_banned_for_real/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;banned anyone who duped&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/x5S9Zcx.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;refunded&lt;/a&gt; anyone who spent real money. The bug was temporarily fixed by reverting the patch note which caused the entire mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let this be a lesson on what happens when you include an untested change at the last minute. You could break an entire economy. Eh, no big deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Super Mario World &#34;Completed&#34; in Under 3 Minutes by Corrupting the RAM</title><link>/2013/03/127-yoshis-in-slot-6/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/127-yoshis-in-slot-6/</guid><description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Syo5sI-iOgY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the video above, you won&amp;rsquo;t regret it. (the fun part starts at 1:12)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tool-Assisted Speed Run&lt;/a&gt; (TAS) of the Super Nintendo classic Super Mario World. TASes use an emulator to perform optimal game actions with frame-by-frame precision in order to complete the game in the lowest amount of time, and can use &amp;ldquo;save states&amp;rdquo; to reverse any gameplay mistakes. Games on older consoles frequently have glitches that require such precision that consequently are very difficult to perform on a console consistently, making TASes more of an art form than actual gameplay advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what the heck is happening in this speedrun? curtmack on Reddit &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1aldvz/major_glitch_discovered_in_luigis_mansion_that/c8yk3g3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;explains it succinctly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for those who are wondering just what the f- happened&amp;hellip; there&amp;rsquo;s a glitch that&amp;rsquo;s been known for a while, where Yoshi can end up in the &amp;ldquo;I have an item in my mouth&amp;rdquo; state, but not actually have an item in his mouth. When he spits out this nothingness, the game crashes. That&amp;rsquo;s all we knew about the glitch&amp;hellip; until recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody decided to take a debugging emulator and step through the crash. He discovered that the crash occurred because the game tried to jump to a specific address in memory, and execute code there. That address did not contain code, and so the system crashed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait a second. What if, by some sheer coincidence, that address &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; contain code? The specific address dropped him in somewhere amongst various data for the game&amp;rsquo;s internal random number generator, and the random number generator can be manipulated in a TAS. Could the game be coerced into running arbitrary code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as it turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s extremely limited. You have the RNG state and a few sprite positions that can be manipulated, but after that is some internal game stuff that can&amp;rsquo;t be. So the length of the &amp;ldquo;program&amp;rdquo; is extremely limited, but as it turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s just long enough to send the signal to the game to switch to the &amp;ldquo;The End&amp;rdquo; screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a related glitch where you can spawn a bouncing fish by doing certain odd things as you spit out an item as Yoshi, and every time a fish bounces, it uses up a randomly-generated number (since it bounces in a random direction). So, putting it all together, you have to spawn a billion fish and have them all bounce a f-jillion times to get the RNG in just the right spot, leave the area, and then fiddle around with some objects to get the last few bits you need in the right place, all while setting up the original spit-nothing glitch in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crazy, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-call-hax&#34;&gt;I Call Hax!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/1945M.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SMW TAS&lt;/a&gt;, posted in 2011, was so crazy that it inspired the creation of a new category of speed runs: &amp;ldquo;Corrupts Memory.&amp;rdquo; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?t=12215&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;discussion on the speed run&lt;/a&gt; provides a technical explanation of of the glitch, which started a debate: &amp;ldquo;does this &lt;em&gt;count&lt;/em&gt; as a speed run?&amp;rdquo; (96% of voters said yes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/smw.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, this is far from the first time where manipulated RAM has been used to complete a game. The classic Nintendo 64 title Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time has the infamous &lt;a href=&#34;http://zeldaspeedruns.com/oot/ba/reverse-bottle-adventure&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reverse Bottle glitch&lt;/a&gt; that allows players to transform items into others, and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/PaUCFrW_mEE?t=13m44s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;memory glitch&lt;/a&gt; that teleports you from the first dungeon to the final cutscene, In &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;/em&gt; on the GameBoy, players discovered how to reprogram the game to &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?p=332488&amp;amp;sid=1d8670bd80327418d202b6608e5cd2a9#332488&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;run arbitrary code&lt;/a&gt;, but many gamers may remember the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Missingno.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Missingno glitch&lt;/a&gt;, which was very easy to reproduce on an actual console and provided many beneficial effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it&amp;rsquo;s not every day that spawning a ton of fishes out of mid-air = victory.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>