<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Personal on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>/categories/personal/</link><description>Recent content in Personal on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 09:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Leaving Apple Inc.</title><link>/2017/05/leaving-apple/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/05/leaving-apple/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working in the San Francisco Bay Area for about 5 years, but I’ve never publicly said where I’ve worked. Well, I was a Software QA Engineer at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Apple Inc.&lt;/a&gt;, on the Applications team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of last week, I handed in my resignation. While I am thankful for the opportunities I have had at Apple, it is time for me to pursue working in other areas I am passionate about and search for other companies to further my personal growth and technical skills. Resigning from a good job to look for something new might defy conventional wisdom, but the time is right for me to make this bold career move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-apple-story&#34;&gt;My Apple Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I graduated with university honors at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt;, from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://tepper.cmu.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tepper School of Business&lt;/a&gt; with a focus on Computing and Information Technology (i.e. data architecture and coding algorithms), and a minor in Statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of my senior year, I received an e-mail from a Software QA Manager at Apple (who followed my &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcommntr.tumblr.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt; at the bottom of &lt;a href=&#34;https://techcrunch.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TechCrunch&lt;/a&gt; articles) inviting me for an on-site interview. Following an offer, I moved to the Bay Area to start my first post-undergrad job in Cupertino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I can&amp;rsquo;t really talk about what I worked on at Apple, I genuinely enjoyed the work, the product, and team. I had a high impact on the final result and I successfully helped qualify many major software releases. However, after a few years, I realized that my technical skill growth was stalling, so I looked for an an internal transfer to another department, ideally in a data analysis/software engineering role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having received no responses internally, I realized I would have to expand my search to outside of Apple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-job-hunt&#34;&gt;My Job Hunt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a strong technical background from my CMU classes, but not having an explicit Computer Science degree has made it difficult to prove aptitude despite my positive annual reviews and proven experience / technical skills at Apple. So I made the decision to blog with a technical focus here at &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;minimaxir.com&lt;/a&gt;, which gave me an avenue to showcase my programmatic skills and the opportunity to self-learn practical new tools not covered during the school curriculum, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;, version control with &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;, and reproducible analyses via &lt;a href=&#34;http://jupyter.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jupyter/IPython Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach has been successful and many readers have liked my my blog posts: often topping &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/dataisbeautiful/comments/4bwr7o/relationship_between_rotten_tomatoes_tomatometer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13429656&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, driving hundreds of thousands of pageviews. Additionally, a couple of my posts were even cited in larger publications such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-intersect/wp/2016/06/30/facebook-news-feed-and-the-tyranny-of-positive-content/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeed.com/tomphillips/photos-that-prove-game-of-thrones-happened-in-real-life&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also published many open-source technical projects to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/big-list-of-naughty-strings&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Big List of Naughty Strings&lt;/a&gt;, a project I made in a couple hours on a weekend inspired by my QA-ing at work, is now at &lt;strong&gt;20,000+ Stars&lt;/strong&gt; on GitHub. My &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-page-post-scraper&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook Page Post Scraper&lt;/a&gt;, which does what the name implies, is now at 1,000+ Stars and has been used by many other businesses and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers have long argued that job seekers should have a strong public portfolio, as demonstrated experience can account for the lack of a relevant degree. After years of building up my portfolio, it became apparent that most outside recruiters I talked with never looked at my blog/GitHub, despite a strong emphasis of both on my résumé.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I subsequently rededicated my blog as a pragmatic demonstration of relevant skills in the data analysis job market, focusing more on practical analysis instead of quirky insights and thoughts. In the process, I obtained proficiency in a number of modern tools, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2016/08/clickbait-cluster/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;interactive data visualizations&lt;/a&gt; on the web with &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Plotly&lt;/a&gt;, processing &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2017/01/amazon-spark/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;big data&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://spark.apache.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Apache Spark&lt;/a&gt;, high-performance &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2017/02/predicting-arrests/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmlc/xgboost&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;xgboost&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Microsoft/LightGBM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LightGBM&lt;/a&gt;, and even &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2017/04/char-embeddings/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;deep learning&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/fchollet/keras&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Keras&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tensorflow/tensorflow&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TensorFlow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now actively looking for a &lt;strong&gt;data analyst/software engineering job within San Francisco&lt;/strong&gt;. If you are interested or if you know of companies who are looking for qualified people, please send me an email at &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:max@minimaxir.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;max@minimaxir.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’ll be using my time over the next couple weeks to openly look for a new job, and to network with others in relevant industries (and be able to interview without taking a day off of work). Things have been improving: my &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=14238066&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; in the Hacker News &amp;ldquo;Who wants to be hired?&amp;rdquo; thread generated many leads who really liked my blog/portfolio. If you’d like to meet up in San Francisco and talk about tech and data stuff, just let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still intend to continue blogging, not as a hobby but in a more purposeful way. I have very ambitious goals and now have more time to execute them at a deeper level. Plans include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web applications leveraging deep learning models, deployed at scale with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;https://kubernetes.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interactive data dashboards accompanying every analytical blog post with &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shiny&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code screencasts at 4k resolution on &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtube.com/minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data analysis live-streaming with augmented functionality on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.twitch.tv/minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have set up a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.patreon.com/minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in order to subsidize my machine learning/deep learning/software/hardware needs for my blog posts. If you have found any of my blog posts useful, a monetary contribution to my Patreon would be appreciated and will be put to good creative use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to keep up with me and my projects, feel free to follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/max.woolf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>