<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Startups on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/categories/startups/</link><description>Recent content in Startups on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://minimaxir.com/categories/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Imgur is Covertly Redirecting Image Links on Facebook and Twitter</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/02/moved-temporarily/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/02/moved-temporarily/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2016 Update&lt;/strong&gt;: I have heard updates that this behavior now occurs on all websites. If you have reproducible steps for this behavior, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://imgur.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Imgur&lt;/a&gt;. Image links without gimmicks. But recently, I noticed that whenever I clicked an Imgur link on Facebook or Twitter, it navigated me to the main image page, with loads of blank empty space and links to other Imgur images instead of just showing me only the image. I double-check the URL, and it indeed begins with the &amp;ldquo;i&amp;rdquo; subdomain that indicates a direct link to the image, such as &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/p9lG2ss.png&amp;quot;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://i.imgur.com/p9lG2ss.png&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, so what&amp;rsquo;s happening?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/imgur_direct.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, when clicking a direct image link for the first time on Facebook, Twitter, and Google+, Imgur will &lt;strong&gt;redirect&lt;/strong&gt; you to the main image page instead. Try clicking the link in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=i.imgur.com&amp;amp;src=typd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;any i.imgur.com URL on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. The main image page has a &amp;ldquo;follow us on Facebook/Twitter!&amp;rdquo; button on desktops, or an advertisement on mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/imgur_link.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This behavior isn&amp;rsquo;t particularly honest and upfront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is Imgur redirecting links from only these social media sites? Are these redirects an accident or are they deliberate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick and dirty way to check is to use the command line. The &lt;em&gt;curl&lt;/em&gt; command loads the data from a specified website. An optional parameter is &lt;em&gt;referrer&lt;/em&gt;, which &amp;ldquo;spoofs&amp;rdquo; the URL of the website where the user is navigating from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say I wanted to &amp;ldquo;access&amp;rdquo; an image direct link coming from a website I know Imgur is not redirecting, such as Reddit. I run this command in the Windows Command Prompt or the Mac Terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl http://i.imgur.com/p9lG2ss.png --referer http://reddit.com -I
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That gives me a Status Code 200, &amp;ldquo;OK&amp;rdquo;, meaning that the image was accessed successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Server: cloudflare-nginx
Date: Wed, 05 Feb 2014 01:41:40 GMT Content-Type: image/png [...]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what happens if the user accesses the link from Facebook or Twitter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl http://i.imgur.com/p9lG2ss.png --referer http://facebook.com -I
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That returns something different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;HTTP/1.1 302 Moved Temporarily
Server: cloudflare-nginx
Date: Wed, 05 Feb 2014 01:44:03 GMT
Content-Type: text/html
[...]
Set-Cookie: __cfduid=dc2e0ae5ee57ff598e079d75fa628f0321391564643058; expires=Mon, 23-Dec-2019 23:50:00 GMT; path=/; domain=.imgur.com; HttpOnly
Location: http://imgur.com/p9lG2ss`
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_302&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Status Code 302&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Moved Temporarily,&amp;rdquo; is the error code for a redirect, and shows that Imgur implemented this behavior intentionally. It also provides the Location of the link to redirect to, in this case the default image page with Imgur&amp;rsquo;s branding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After checking all popular social media sites (and their respective URL shortners) as referrers against Imgur&amp;rsquo;s direct image links, I determined that the only referrer domains that Imgur redirects are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://facebook.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://facebook.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://twitter.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://t.co&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://t.co&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://plus.google.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://plus.google.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to share your cat photos and .gifs directly to friends, I guess you can still share them on LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t say that what Imgur is doing is unethical; many startups use redirects to trap users and spam them with popups saying JOIN MY WEBSITE. At the least, your friends still get to see the image you linked. It&amp;rsquo;s understandable why Imgur would use the redirects; direct image links cause them to lose money through bandwidth expense and earn none, while links to normal image pages make it apparent that the image is from Imgur, and the company could get new users from the branding. Many, many more direct links are made than indirect links, as shown in the image at the beginning of the article, and that can account for a lot of lost revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that redirecting users without disclosure is the start of a slippery slope. When I post a direct image link by copying the &amp;ldquo;Direct Link&amp;rdquo; URL, I &lt;em&gt;expect&lt;/em&gt; that others who use the link will also see the direct image. But that&amp;rsquo;s not the case if the link is posted on Facebook or Twitter. Additionally, the redirects make the images take &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; longer to load on mobile, since loading the scripts and ads slow the entire page down. Making it so that the redirect is only seen the first time an image is viewed doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer much solace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the redirects are successful at converting new users for Imgur, what&amp;rsquo;s stopping them from redirecting other sites? I strongly hope that Imgur won&amp;rsquo;t turn into the next Photobucket or Imageshack, but whenever a startup does something weird and not transparent, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Friends Of My Friends Are Not My Friends</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2014/01/farcical-friends-of-friends-folly/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2014/01/farcical-friends-of-friends-folly/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jelly.co/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jelly&lt;/a&gt;, a highly-anticipated social networking app by Twitter co-founder Biz Stone, was released last week. One of Jelly&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.jelly.co/post/72563498393/introducing-jelly&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;underlying principles&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;it’s not hard to imagine that the true promise of a connected society is people helping each other.&amp;rdquo; While using Jelly over the past few days, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people ask whether or not to exercise, make unsubtle plugs for their product, sell a car Craigslist-style, and get amnesia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/jellyposts2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, what? How are these questions representative of &amp;ldquo;a connected society,&amp;rdquo; especially since I don&amp;rsquo;t know any of the question authors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jelly tells its users that they can &amp;ldquo;help friends, or friends-of-friends with their questions.&amp;rdquo; The vast majority of the questions I&amp;rsquo;ve seen are from Friends of Friends. I&amp;rsquo;m Facebook Friends with people who have &lt;strong&gt;thousands&lt;/strong&gt; of friends; the probability that I have something in common with those second-degree friends is low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Websites like Jelly and even Facebook are now utilizing the content made by second-degree &amp;ldquo;friends.&amp;rdquo; Why am I seeing pictures and statuses from friends of friends, who are essentially complete strangers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook-s-farcical-friends-of-friends-folly&#34;&gt;Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Farcical Friends of Friends Folly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple months ago, Facebook again tweaked the News Feed algorithm such that all new Posts on a friend&amp;rsquo;s Wall are shown on your News Feed, even if the person making the Post is a complete stranger to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, Facebook showed posts in your News Feed that were posted on a Friend&amp;rsquo;s wall only if they were made by another Friend. If you are friends with both people, there&amp;rsquo;s likely a common link between all three of you, such as going to the same college or working at the same company. That can make the Wall post more relevant to your interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, people have many social circles. What happens when a stranger not in any of my social circles posts on a Friend&amp;rsquo;s wall?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post recently appeared in my News Feed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/fb-stranger-wall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know who the person with &amp;ldquo;1 mutual friend&amp;rdquo; is. (the &amp;ldquo;1 mutual friend&amp;rdquo; being the friend who received the post). I don&amp;rsquo;t live in Arizona. Why am I seeing this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I may be Facebook Friends with someone, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean I should be Friends with their Friends. Facebook is showing me Posts that aren&amp;rsquo;t relevant to me at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This behavior also extends to your Friends&amp;rsquo; birthday: all &amp;ldquo;Happy Birthday!&amp;rdquo; posts on your Friend&amp;rsquo;s Wall also display in your News Feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This entry was visible on my News Feed for an entire day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/mutual-friends-birthday.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; wants you to wish your Friends happy birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t need to see strangers with &amp;ldquo;1 mutual friend&amp;rdquo; wish my friends Happy Birthday. It&amp;rsquo;s just extra clutter on an already cluttered News Feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, other websites such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; push second-degree friends. Twitter&amp;rsquo;s new &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/i/discover&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Discover&lt;/a&gt; feature highlights users who the people you Follow are themselves Following. LinkedIn shows your connections&amp;rsquo; new connections so you can form connections with them too. But the difference between Twitter/LinkedIn and Facebook/Jelly is that both Facebook and Jelly push the power of &lt;strong&gt;intimate&lt;/strong&gt; friendships, and imposing a sense of intimacy between strangers feels fake and intrudes on actual friendships.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Do startups with short names containing few vowels raise more money?</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 07:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One reason startups use crazy and bizarre names like &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NegaCycl&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Filtrzzz&lt;/a&gt; is to ensure that their name is unique, making it easier to acquire the .com domain name and Twitter handle for their startup. Another reason is to make their startup sound &lt;em&gt;kewl&lt;/em&gt; and theoretically make the name more memorable in the minds of users and potential investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dakwak, Wibki, Zeef, Funifi. These aren&amp;rsquo;t random words: these are funded startups which were featured at &lt;a href=&#34;http://startupalley.techcrunch.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TechCrunch Disrupt Startup Alley 2013&lt;/a&gt;. And then you have startups such as Lyft, SCVNGR, and Fastly, which have all raised &lt;em&gt;tens of millions of dollars&lt;/em&gt; in venture capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do startups with these short, low-vowel names actually raise more money than startups with traditional names?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the association between the length of words in the English language and the number of vowels that they contain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/english-words.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the English language, the majority of the words have 8 letters, with 3 of those letters being vowels. (8,3) is also the center of the density distribution for the heat map, spreading outward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s compare the vowel distribution of normal English words to the distribution of the names of startups that have successfully raised venture capital, in order to identify just how many funded startups have quirky names:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/count-startups.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, the two distributions are nearly identical! Both graphs are centered at about (8,3), radiating outward. This implies that the number of startups with uniquely-constructed names are outliers and not the typical names for startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t answer the core question: sure, fewer funded startups have weird names relative to the amount of total funded startups, but do they raise more money on average than startups with typical names?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/mean-startups-fund.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no discernible pattern for the average amount raised, unlike with the previous two charts. For the vast majority of the possible combinations of name length and $ vowels, the range of capital raised is between $5M and $25M. There are higher values at the lower-end of the graph (low length, low vowels), but that can be attributed to the relatively low amount of startup data for those combinations to smooth out the average. (e.g. the $78M spike at 3 length, 2 vowels is due to the always-lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crunchbase.com/company/aol&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;AOL&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://googlepress.blogspot.com/2005/12/time-warners-aol-and-google-to-expand_20.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;$1 billion investment from Google&lt;/a&gt;, and there are only 15 other startups in the segment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the statistical correlation between name length and funding, number of vowels and funding, and ratio of length to vowels and funding, are all effectively &lt;strong&gt;zero&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, quirky startup names may make it easier to find a domain name, but it won&amp;rsquo;t necessarily give an edge in the investment process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data for English words from &lt;a href=&#34;http://wordlist.sourceforge.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kevin&amp;rsquo;s Word List Page&lt;/a&gt;, and data for the startup names/funding from &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.crunchbase.com/about/crunchbase-data-exports/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CrunchBase&amp;rsquo;s September Data Export&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>1 in 3 Links Submitted To Reddit Go To Imgur Or YouTube</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2013 10:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;, you may have noticed that many link submissions go to &amp;ldquo;imgur.com&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://imgur.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Imgur&lt;/a&gt;, an image hosting service that launched on Reddit a few years ago and has seen outstanding growth ever since, even &lt;a href=&#34;http://venturebeat.com/2013/09/26/imgur-traffic-milestone-100m-uniques/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;surpassing Reddit itself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how many of Reddit&amp;rsquo;s many, many links are actually links to Imgur? As it turns out, Imgur, along with YouTube, account for &lt;em&gt;32%&lt;/em&gt; of the links submitted to Reddit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Reddit&amp;rsquo;s API, I have downloaded about 5 million link submissions from Reddit, accounting for nearly two months of activity from July 22nd to September 26th. I complied a list of the most-frequent link destination domains for the links submitted anywhere on Reddit. The results were interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/links722_926.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imgur domains (i.imgur.com and imgur.com) account for &lt;strong&gt;23.7%&lt;/strong&gt; of all links submitted to Reddit, and the YouTube domains (youtube.com and youtu.be) account for &lt;strong&gt;8.2%&lt;/strong&gt; of all links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two websites account for &lt;strong&gt;32%&lt;/strong&gt; of all links submitted to Reddit (i.e. 1 in every 3 submitted links go to Imgur or YouTube), and no other website is remotely close. Not the meme sites, not the music sites, not the news sites, not the &lt;em&gt;porn&lt;/em&gt; sites: Reddit is images and video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; on Reddit are the Imgur and YouTube links most prominent?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a chart of the top subreddits, by percentage of all Imgur links submitted on Reddit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/imgur722_926.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting to note how the &lt;em&gt;funny&lt;/em&gt; subreddit has more Imgur links than the &lt;em&gt;pics&lt;/em&gt; subreddit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For YouTube, and the percentage of all YouTube links submitted on Reddit by subreddit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/youtube722_926.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Videos&lt;/em&gt; wins as you might expect, but &lt;em&gt;Music&lt;/em&gt; is in second place. Along with &lt;em&gt;listentothis&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;Metal&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;hiphopheads&lt;/em&gt;, YouTube is the de facto website for &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt; as well as video. Gaming is also very popular with YouTube links, with &lt;em&gt;gaming&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;leagueoflegends&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Minecraft&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images and video are the backbone of Reddit, and both Imgur and YouTube are the primary sources. Although, there appears to be a nontrivial demand for pure music websites such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt; and gaming video websites such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitch.tv/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitch.tv&lt;/a&gt; &amp;hellip;could there be another big success story in the making?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The tabulated data used to create each of the three charts is located at &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGxoVGFyX19hV2paMk5lOFRvNXlkcnc&amp;amp;usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this Google Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; for your perusal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Which Universities Produce the Most Successful Startup Founders?</title><link>https://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 10:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;If you read startup funding announcements on tech blogs frequently, you&amp;rsquo;ve may have noticed that these startup founders have often attended prestigious universities. Founders who have graduated from Ivy League schools, such as Harvard, Yale and Princeton, unsurprisingly raise millions for their startups. Of course, top tier tech schools such as Stanford, MIT, and Carnegie Mellon foster a strong technical and entrepreneurial background: attributes which venture capitalists seek when investing in a startup founder. &lt;em&gt;(Disclosure: I&amp;rsquo;m a Carnegie Mellon alumnus)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the tech universities produce more funded graduates than the Ivy League universities? Do the founders from Ivy League Universities receive more funding than those from the top tier tech universities?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using TechCrunch&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crunchbase.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CrunchBase&lt;/a&gt; API, I obtained the data of about 2,500 startup founders in the United States who have created a startup which has received investment from venture capitalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that data, I found some rather interesting trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-universities-produced-the-most-amount-of-graduates-who-have-received-funding&#34;&gt;Which universities produced the most amount of graduates who have received funding?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of university graduates attempt to make a startup, but most will not succeed. Are the graduates of some universities more frequently successful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the Top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/founder-colleges.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stanford has the most amount of funded graduates, which is unsurprising as it&amp;rsquo;s located in the Silicon Valley heart of venture capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven out of the eight Ivy League Universities (colored green on the chart) are present, but most of the Ivies are in the middle of the chart. MIT and UC Berkeley each have nearly &lt;em&gt;double&lt;/em&gt; the amount of successful graduates from Yale and Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that Tel Aviv University, an Israeli university, ties Duke University at 21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-university-s-graduates-have-cumulatively-raised-the-most-amount-of-total-funding&#34;&gt;Which university&amp;rsquo;s graduates have cumulatively raised the most amount of total funding?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to measure success is through the success of the founders&amp;rsquo; subsequent startups and the amount of venture capital they have raised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the Top 8 universities whose graduates have received the most amount of funding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/sum-funding.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard and Stanford graduates are very close in terms of total funding raised. However, there&amp;rsquo;s a clear &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Power Law&lt;/a&gt; in effect, as those two along with UC Berkeley, have produced founders who&amp;rsquo;ve generated much, much more venture funding than those of the other universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-university-s-graduates-raise-the-most-amount-of-money-in-their-first-round-of-funding-on-average&#34;&gt;Which university&amp;rsquo;s graduates raise the most amount of money in their first round of funding on average?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Startup founders with big, world changing ideas need lots of venture capital. Only the founders with &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; ideas will actually receive it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the average amount of first-round funding for the top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://minimaxir.com/img/avg-first-raised.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carnegie Mellon and Princeton, which had a relatively low number of funded founders and a relatively low number of total capital raised, instead have a &lt;em&gt;significantly&lt;/em&gt; higher amount of average first funding. UCLA also placed. Perhaps the students from these three universities tend to have more ambitious startup ideas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, Stanford and Harvard appear to be the kings of startups. They have the most amount of graduates, and the most amount of total venture capital raised. The tech blogs would surely consider that a success, but could the greater funding for CMU/Princeton lead to the creation of the next billion-dollar startup? We can only wait and see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE: As pointed out by robotcookies on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6075862&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;corresponding Hacker News thread&lt;/a&gt;, I missed UCLA in the first draft, which had 29 funded graduates. The charts have been updated.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are welcome to use the founder data from CrunchBase by &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddEV1LUpaQUVsdmJYcERoM0FNU3lPcVE&amp;amp;usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;viewing the data on Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;, or by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/3jz2wsr4d6fc4t6/founders_w_college.csv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;downloading the raw CSV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;University data was standardized to make analysis easier (e.g. for Carnegie Mellon, the founders who listed their institution as &amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;CMU,&amp;rdquo; all had their institution changed to be &amp;ldquo;CMU&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chart #1 measures unique founders, so it does not double-count a founder who has founded more than one funded startup.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chart #2 assumes equal contribution of each founder to the funding: if a startup has a total funding of $100,000 with 2 founders, the amount used for the chart will be $50,000 for each founder.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chart #3 ignores startup data for the chart which has a Series B, Series C, or Series D listed as their first round on CrunchBase, or if the amount raised was not provided.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>