<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hacks on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</title><link>/tags/hacks/</link><description>Recent content in Hacks on Max Woolf&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Max Woolf &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 20:50:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/hacks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Profanity-Laced Video Game Password That Breaks Everything</title><link>/2013/05/its-a-livin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2013 20:50:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/its-a-livin/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/metroidboxart.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of video games, you&amp;rsquo;ve likely heard of the Metroid franchise. Released for the NES in 1986 by Nintendo, Metroid set a new standard for 2-D exploration in video games with its expansive power-up system, well-hidden secrets, and polished platforming controls. Due to its popularity, Metroid has been rereleased multiple times: as an unlockable in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Prime&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metroid Prime&lt;/a&gt;, an unlockable in the remake &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Zero_Mission&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metroid: Zero Mission&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classic_NES_Series&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;standalone game&lt;/a&gt; on the Game Boy Advance, the Wii Virtual Console, and the 3DS Virtual Console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You play as Samus Aran, an armored bounty hunter who has infiltrated the base of the dreaded Space Pirates on Planet Zebes. Samus must defeat the leaders of the Space Pirates: the dinosaur Kraid, the dragon and memetic badass of the series &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridley_(Metroid)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ridley&lt;/a&gt;, and the AI construct &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_Brain_(Metroid)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mother Brain&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, Samus must find a way to defeat the Metroids, which are nearly-indestructible parasites that threaten all life. Yes, this was a plot written in the 80&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the NES Metroid cartridge did not have the ability to save games, and the game itself took awhile to complete, Nintendo developed a password system to allow players to continue at a later time. Upon death, the player received a 24-character alphanumeric password that could be entered to restore all items the player has unlocked and remember which bosses the player has defeated. Most of these passwords were gibberish that required a pen-and-paper to write down and remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One password, however, is more memorable, and much more sinister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-password-is-always-swordfish&#34;&gt;The Password is Always Swordfish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the days of the internet and personal computing, players &lt;a href=&#34;http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/List_of_Metroid_passwords&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;found passwords&lt;/a&gt; with unique properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Narpas_Sword&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Narpas Sword password&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/narpassword.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is essentially the debug mode for the game, with all items unlocked, infinite health, and infinite health for Samus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, more revealing password is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Justin_Bailey&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Justin Bailey password&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justinbailey.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This password starts the game with most unlockables obtained, but more notably, it changes Samus&amp;rsquo;s sprite from an armored powersuit to a bikini swimsuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One password, discovered over 20 years later, long after the Metroid password system had been completely reverse-engineered, does not grant you all items. &lt;em&gt;This&lt;/em&gt; password just crashes and resets the game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/engageridley.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wtf&#34;&gt;WTF?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a NES and various other rereleases, inputting that code will cause the game to either simply reset or transform the game into a glitched wonderland:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x3UyVylP7AI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what happens when you enter the password on an emulated Virtual Console, where the game environment is sandboxed? In the case of the 3DS Virtual Console, the &lt;em&gt;3DS completely crashes&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/pjQ7SjB_6a8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rated-e-for-everyone&#34;&gt;Rated E for Everyone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be asking &amp;ldquo;did someone at Nintendo actually program a consequence for profanity in the game? Is the glitching and crashing a punishment for the perverse player?&amp;rdquo; In truth, the password is merely a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, the password algorithm for Metroid has been reverse-engineered, and you can actually download a program to both generate and interpret such passwords &lt;a href=&#34;http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/metroidpassgen.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The profane password is indeed a legitimate password (in which Ridley is already defeated, ironically enough). But why does it crash the game? The &lt;a href=&#34;http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/password.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metroid Password Format Guide&lt;/a&gt; explains the secret:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are five valid start locations. They are specified using bits 64-66.
To start in Brinstar, all the bits should be off. Norfair, Kraid&amp;rsquo;s Lair, and
Ridley&amp;rsquo;s Lair can be specified by turning their bit on and leaving the others
off. Tourian is specified by turning on Norfair and Kraid&amp;rsquo;s Lair
simultaneously. Any other combination of these three bits is invalid and will
cause Metroid to reset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reset bit is part of the start location. There are 16 possible values,
but only 5 valid ones. Turning on the reset bit will produce and invalid
start location and cause Metroid to reset. This is why it is called it is
called the reset bit, because it guarantees an invalid password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the profane password, the reset bit is turned on, so it will always cause a reset. And that&amp;rsquo;s why the weird behavior happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you manually disable the reset bit using this tool in order to make the password valid, the new password becomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/metroidpassgen2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not as catchy, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the Justin Bailey password is also a completely coincidental password. Sometimes, passwords can just do very unexpected things.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Super Mario World &#34;Completed&#34; in Under 3 Minutes by Corrupting the RAM</title><link>/2013/03/127-yoshis-in-slot-6/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/127-yoshis-in-slot-6/</guid><description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Syo5sI-iOgY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the video above, you won&amp;rsquo;t regret it. (the fun part starts at 1:12)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tool-Assisted Speed Run&lt;/a&gt; (TAS) of the Super Nintendo classic Super Mario World. TASes use an emulator to perform optimal game actions with frame-by-frame precision in order to complete the game in the lowest amount of time, and can use &amp;ldquo;save states&amp;rdquo; to reverse any gameplay mistakes. Games on older consoles frequently have glitches that require such precision that consequently are very difficult to perform on a console consistently, making TASes more of an art form than actual gameplay advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what the heck is happening in this speedrun? curtmack on Reddit &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1aldvz/major_glitch_discovered_in_luigis_mansion_that/c8yk3g3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;explains it succinctly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for those who are wondering just what the f- happened&amp;hellip; there&amp;rsquo;s a glitch that&amp;rsquo;s been known for a while, where Yoshi can end up in the &amp;ldquo;I have an item in my mouth&amp;rdquo; state, but not actually have an item in his mouth. When he spits out this nothingness, the game crashes. That&amp;rsquo;s all we knew about the glitch&amp;hellip; until recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody decided to take a debugging emulator and step through the crash. He discovered that the crash occurred because the game tried to jump to a specific address in memory, and execute code there. That address did not contain code, and so the system crashed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait a second. What if, by some sheer coincidence, that address &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; contain code? The specific address dropped him in somewhere amongst various data for the game&amp;rsquo;s internal random number generator, and the random number generator can be manipulated in a TAS. Could the game be coerced into running arbitrary code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as it turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s extremely limited. You have the RNG state and a few sprite positions that can be manipulated, but after that is some internal game stuff that can&amp;rsquo;t be. So the length of the &amp;ldquo;program&amp;rdquo; is extremely limited, but as it turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s just long enough to send the signal to the game to switch to the &amp;ldquo;The End&amp;rdquo; screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a related glitch where you can spawn a bouncing fish by doing certain odd things as you spit out an item as Yoshi, and every time a fish bounces, it uses up a randomly-generated number (since it bounces in a random direction). So, putting it all together, you have to spawn a billion fish and have them all bounce a f-jillion times to get the RNG in just the right spot, leave the area, and then fiddle around with some objects to get the last few bits you need in the right place, all while setting up the original spit-nothing glitch in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crazy, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-call-hax&#34;&gt;I Call Hax!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/1945M.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SMW TAS&lt;/a&gt;, posted in 2011, was so crazy that it inspired the creation of a new category of speed runs: &amp;ldquo;Corrupts Memory.&amp;rdquo; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?t=12215&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;discussion on the speed run&lt;/a&gt; provides a technical explanation of of the glitch, which started a debate: &amp;ldquo;does this &lt;em&gt;count&lt;/em&gt; as a speed run?&amp;rdquo; (96% of voters said yes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/smw.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, this is far from the first time where manipulated RAM has been used to complete a game. The classic Nintendo 64 title Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time has the infamous &lt;a href=&#34;http://zeldaspeedruns.com/oot/ba/reverse-bottle-adventure&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reverse Bottle glitch&lt;/a&gt; that allows players to transform items into others, and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/PaUCFrW_mEE?t=13m44s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;memory glitch&lt;/a&gt; that teleports you from the first dungeon to the final cutscene, In &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;/em&gt; on the GameBoy, players discovered how to reprogram the game to &lt;a href=&#34;http://tasvideos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?p=332488&amp;amp;sid=1d8670bd80327418d202b6608e5cd2a9#332488&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;run arbitrary code&lt;/a&gt;, but many gamers may remember the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Missingno.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Missingno glitch&lt;/a&gt;, which was very easy to reproduce on an actual console and provided many beneficial effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it&amp;rsquo;s not every day that spawning a ton of fishes out of mid-air = victory.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Let Myspace&#39;s Justin Timberlake Bring Sexy To The Entire Internet</title><link>/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 21:36:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;TechCrunch writer Sarah Perez recently wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/15/lost-on-new-myspace-cant-escape-justin-send-help/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;an incredibly hilarious article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;https://new.myspace.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Myspace&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s recent redesign, and the&amp;hellip;overemphasis of a certain former N&amp;rsquo;Sync band member. Justin Timberlake, the spearhead of Myspace&amp;rsquo;s music-oriented redesign, stresses his clean-shaven image with a handsome yet somber black-and-white portrait that always seems to follow you where you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m OK with this. There are certainly far &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2012/03/ethics-self-promotion/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ways to promote a startup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His moody yet charmful face adds a touch of class to any website. But why does he have to stay constrained to Myspace? Why not let Justin Timberlake dominate the world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-such-thing-as-too-much-sexy&#34;&gt;No Such Thing As Too Much Sexy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this post on a desktop or laptop, you&amp;rsquo;ll see a handsome fellow in the lower-right corner. This is Justin Timberlake of the Mickey Mouse Club. Say hi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the power of the Stylish extension for Chrome and Firefox, Mr. Timberlake has already made his mark on many startups around the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest9.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest8.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest7.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/justintest4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this magic, I use the Stylish browser extension, which can be used with either &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/stylish/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;. I have used Stylish &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;before, with browser filters&lt;/a&gt;, and it worked very well. If you want your own moody Justin, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the Stylish extension for your browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the extension preferences, go to &amp;ldquo;Managed Installed Styles&amp;rdquo; and select &amp;ldquo;Write New Style&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste this CSS code in the &amp;ldquo;Code&amp;rdquo; textbox:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;body, ._li, .main {
background-image: url(http://i.imgur.com/UN5HE.png) !important;
background-position: right bottom !important;
background-repeat: no-repeat !important;
background-attachment: fixed !important;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you&amp;rsquo;re done! Justin will appear pretty much everywhere. Yes, there are a lot of &lt;em&gt;!important&lt;/em&gt; declarations, but Justin Timberlake is an important man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, by using the HTML snippet in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/display-justin-timberlake-sexiness&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;, you can add Justin to your own site!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to narrow down the domains where Justin appears by using Stylish as necessary. Although, why would you do such a thing!?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;taking-justin-to-the-next-level&#34;&gt;Taking Justin To The Next Level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/816440400_1965379.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we can make Justin appear anywhere, let&amp;rsquo;s put his power to good use. TechCrunch writer Alexia Tsostis recently made a post about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/16/were-bringing-techcrunch-back/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;upcoming redesign of TechCrunch&lt;/a&gt;, which, I admit, is long overdue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the post, Alexia spoils that the redesign will include lots of sparkles. And a picture of the Justin-man himself. Above is a mockup made by Chris Velazco, another TechCrunch writer, and it is indeed marvelous. (except for the lack of a comments section!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why wait for the redesign? We have Timberlake Technology. We can do it &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the power of Stylish, I present to you, a sneak peek into TechCrunch&amp;rsquo;s 2013 redesign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a &lt;em&gt;few&lt;/em&gt; stylistic additions as well. It&amp;rsquo;s magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/j6m2pjjhnuU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a copy of the CSS I used to emulate this wonderful layout in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/minimaxir/techcrunch-1999&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will you let Timberlake enrich &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; life? He&amp;rsquo;s waiting. In the lower-right corner of your screen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Auto-Save Images From Reddit To Computer Without Visiting The Site (Using IFTTT)</title><link>/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2013 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/</guid><description>
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2016 Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Yahoo Pipes is dead and IFTTT now supports a Reddit channel, which allows you to duplicate this functionality.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR: Use this &lt;a href=&#34;https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IFTTT recipe&lt;/a&gt;, and change the subreddit value in the parameter of the Feed URL as needed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I joked about a hypothetical social media strategy in which an automated script does Facebook brand management by stealing the top cute images from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; - an aggregator of trending topics and images - and reposting them on the Facebook page, additionally adding a cute message encouraging users to LIKE, SHARE, and COMMENT! We get easy social media fame for no monetary cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of curiosity, I wanted to see if it was feasible to create such a script. Both Reddit and Facebook indeed have APIs that make it easy. But then I have to set up a server to check Reddit periodically, ensure that no images are duplicated, etc., and that can take time to implement and ensure that it works correctly (&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the images must be cute!). I looked into &lt;a href=&#34;https://ifttt.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IFTTT&lt;/a&gt;, a relatively new startup that talks between different popular web services to automate simple tasks, like posting to Twitter whenever you post to Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, yes, this is possible, and you can also save the top images on Reddit to your computer via any cloud storage service without ever visiting the website too! Just use &lt;a href=&#34;https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this IFTTT recipe&lt;/a&gt;! There are a few interesting caveats, though&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-simple-syndication-is-really-simple&#34;&gt;Really Simple Syndication is&amp;hellip;Really Simple?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/redditrss2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IFTTT allows users to extract information from RSS feeds, which one might typically be used to read blogs and news articles. The RSS feed typically provides the title, author, date, and content of a post: the important things. However, RSS has more applications: it can distribute other data, such as weather and desktop wallpapers. IFTTT allows other apps to load image and audio files from an RSS feed, but only if the RSS feed link links to the content itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this won&amp;rsquo;t work on Reddit by default, as its RSS feeds do not contain a direct link to the photo and instead link to the Reddit comments on the image. Image-based websites, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BuzzFeed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://interfacelift.com/wallpaper/downloads/date/any/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;InterfaceLift&lt;/a&gt; also implement a similar system because they don&amp;rsquo;t want their users just to use a script to download images and bypass the website and its lovely revenue-generating advertisements. Therefore, the RSS feed alone won&amp;rsquo;t work with IFTTT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my research into my social media exploitation hypothesis, I found a &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.stevemould.com/rss-feed-reddit-stories-score-threshold/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog post by Steve Mould&lt;/a&gt; that provides a way to translate data from Reddit&amp;rsquo;s JSON API to an RSS feed using a service called &lt;a href=&#34;http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yahoo Pipes&lt;/a&gt;. This modified RSS feed, when given a subreddit and a score threshold, obtains the top Reddit posts in that subreddit above that karma threshold (upvotes - downvotes), and returns a feed item which contains direct link to the referenced URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/W1ypdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my variation of his Reddit Pipe&lt;/a&gt;. My script to process the API has a few changes (such as using Reddit&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;hot&amp;rdquo; posts, instead of the top posts; hot posts update much more frequently). Testing it with r/aww and a threshold of 50 karma, I received 177 very cute pictures on my computer in a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/redditcute.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that Pipe, you can get the data in a RSS feed URL. Right-click and copy that feed URL into a IFTTT recipe as the source. For the action, use the &lt;strong&gt;{{EntryURL}}&lt;/strong&gt; variable to retrieve the image URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;with-great-power-comes-great-cuteness&#34;&gt;With Great Power Comes Great Cuteness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can save the Reddit images to your computer automatically using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt;. Or &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;. Or &lt;a href=&#34;https://skydrive.live.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SkyDrive&lt;/a&gt;. Or even get a cute email every hour!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to IFTTT, there are many other creative things you can do with the feed that you can include in a recipe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto-post the image to your Tumblr or WordPress blog. Easy cuteness, and you&amp;rsquo;ll be the source!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto-curate the cute photos to your Facebook or Twitter account. All your friends will love you!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get social media fame for no additional monetary cost by publishing the cute images to your Facebook Page, with an encouragement to LIKE SHARE and COMMENT! My original hypothesis was correct!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/redditnega.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One caveat in using Yahoo Pipes is that it is rate limited to 200 runs in a 10 minute interval, meaning that the IFTTT recipe provided will likely fail if more than 200 people use the feed. If that does happen, just clone my pipe, and use the RSS feed from the clone for your own personal recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, there&amp;rsquo;s no rate limiting on when recipes are triggered and images are posted/downloaded. You can trigger multiple images simultaneously, which may be considered spammy if you are posting to social media. In that case, increase the karma threshold to reduce the frequency of the postings and to maintain a high quality of the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/iftttrecipe.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting socially-vetted photos on your computer without any effort is a useful timesaver. A solution to a first world problem, perhaps, but it&amp;rsquo;s the little things that count!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Do Many Tweets Begin With A Period?</title><link>/2013/01/prefixed-period/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 21:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/01/prefixed-period/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a Twitter fanatic. Although I do have &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/minimaxir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; with about 300 followers, Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Subscribe feature &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/max.woolf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;on my Facebook profile&lt;/a&gt; has met my use case for publishing sarcastic quips and cool links for a broad audience over the internet. I mostly use my Twitter account to read tweets from tech columnists, yet I don&amp;rsquo;t even comment on their tweets because &lt;strong&gt;tweets that are replies to someone are not visible in the home timeline of my followers&lt;/strong&gt;. I can understand the intuition behind this behavior: Twitter conversations can contain a lot of low-content tweets, and Twitter doesn&amp;rsquo;t want its users to be spammed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that many tweets from actual Twitter fanatics begin with a prefixed period, such as *&amp;ldquo;.@minimaxir wow funny joke!&amp;rdquo; *and &lt;em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.@minimaxir is a huge dork!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. I thought the dot was a typo, until I noticed many people also prefixing the period, seemingly randomly, in their own tweets. All of those tweets seemed like witty replies that begged for mass exposure, and so I eventually realized that beginning your reply Tweet with a period (.) allows it to be seen by all your followers. **Otherwise, only the replyee will receive notification of the reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having your reply tweets appear to your followers only if you begin them with a prefixed period is not intuitive at all. And this particular behavior and its workaround are not documented in &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.twitter.com/groups/31-twitter-basics/topics/109-tweets-messages/articles/14023-what-are-replies-and-mentions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&amp;rsquo;s help docs&lt;/a&gt;. And replying to tweets is a core feature of Twitter. How many users would be able to deduce this behavior? How many brands, who rely on user engagement, are even aware of this behavior?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I was only partially correct. It&amp;rsquo;s even &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;xy-z&#34;&gt;XY = @(Z)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/twitter2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ScottyLabs/status/286921265514700801&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a tweet&lt;/a&gt; in my timeline that had a prefixed period, but clearly was not a reply to anyone. Confused, I pointed out that prefixed periods aren&amp;rsquo;t necessary if the tweet is not a reply. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amyquispe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Amy Quispe&lt;/a&gt;, founder of ScottyLabs and a CS senior at Carnegie Mellon University with much more startup knowledge than myself, pointed out that I was wrong, and &lt;strong&gt;if the tweet begins with a @, it will not appear in your follower&amp;rsquo;s timelines, regardless of whether it&amp;rsquo;s a reply or a mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who tweets, for example, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;@SHO_Dexter is my favorite television show! Season 7 was AWESOME!!!&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;, will likely not have that tweet seen by any of their followers. Therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s incredibly easy, and incredibly likely, for that behavior to unintentionally trigger a false positive for spam. Again, would a person notice that one of his/her tweets is not being seen? It&amp;rsquo;s bad for the user, and it&amp;rsquo;s even bad for @SHO_Dexter, who misses out on the free advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; *correction** was still only partially correct*, as there&amp;rsquo;s one more important caveat:** if a tweet by X begins a tweet with an @ mention of Y, and if Z is a follower of &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; X and Y, then Z will see the tweet. If the second condition is not true, then Z will not see the tweet.**&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is apparently a course in deductive reasoning. To be fair, this caveat is clearly stated in the help docs, and this behavior makes sense in the context of mutual friends among users. Nevertheless, it&amp;rsquo;s not intuitive at all, and it&amp;rsquo;s mostly irrelevant: a prefixed period tweet reaches all of your followers, 100% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pestilent-prefixed-period-problem&#34;&gt;The Pestilent Prefixed Period Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter users want maximum reach. Brands want maximum reach. Therefore, everyone will use the prefixed period for replies and mentions. Those who don&amp;rsquo;t use prefixed periods on Twitter will be left behind in this cutthroat game of social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two problems with encouraging prefixed periods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It alienates newcomers to Twitter. Some online communities do have unwritten behaviors: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;, for example, invokes &amp;ldquo;vote fuzzing&amp;rdquo; on popular posts, which disguises the true amount of upvotes and downvotes on any particular post by adding fake upvotes/downvotes. You won&amp;rsquo;t find that in any Reddit documentation, which leads to the frequent outbursts of &amp;ldquo;WHO THE HELL WOULD DOWNVOTE THIS PUPPY?&amp;rdquo; Quirks like these don&amp;rsquo;t make communities exclusive: it makes them insular.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It looks tacky and ugly&lt;/strong&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s not a trivial complaint. Every @mention tweet looks like someone made a typo. I don&amp;rsquo;t think that&amp;rsquo;s the brand image Twitter wants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could Twitter address this? An option would be to adopt a system similar to Facebook&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; post visibility settings, and allow users to set the reach of an individual tweet as necessary. Another option is to have an &lt;em&gt;All your replies and @mentions are shown to all your followers&lt;/em&gt; account option that is opt-in, and let the user&amp;rsquo;s followers determine whether the content is spam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter, with an impending IPO, needs to help potential newcomers out in any way possible. Eliminating the need for prefixed periods is a great start to increasing accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS: I am not a huge dork.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>